our project

project overview

The Grimms’ Fairy Tales were published in 1812 contained 86 tales, which were to pay tribute to the German culture. The goal for these stories was not for them to become bedtime stories. During the early 1800s, the Napoleonic Wars inspired them to write and share these stores to display and preserve their heritage of their country. The Grimm Brothers, Jacob (1785-1863) and Wilhem (1786-1859) Grimm were born into a fairly wealthy family, until their father died in 1796. After this, they were forced to pave their own path. The brothers attended the University of Marburg and were to study law and continue their civic duty, like their father, but their love for language and country overtook their interests. The tales have since been translated from German to English. The German Tales that have been explored here are the orginial 1812 versions, and the equivalent English Tales that are from D. L. Ashliman, which were translated from 1998-2020. The scope of this project is to compare the original German Tales to the translated English version. We are focusing on the female characters to determine these comparisons. A major distinction between these versions is the difference in time period. This leads us to questions, such as how are women portrayed differently, if they are? Our analysis of these tales have lead us to better understand how time and culture is a factor in these versions of the Grimms’ Fairy Tales.

sources

fairy tale texts:

https://sites.pitt.edu/~dash/grimm.html

biographical information:

https://www.nationalgeographic.co.uk/history-and-civilisation/2019/09/brothers-grimm-fairy-tales-were-never-meant-kids

Cinderella

German Version

English Version

Es war einmal ein reicher Mann, der leb- te lange Zeit vergnügt mit seiner Frau, und sie hatten ein einziges Töchterlein zusammen. Da ward die Frau krank, und als sie todtkrank ward, rief sie ihre Tochter und sagte: „liebes Kind, ich muß dich verlassen, aber wenn ich oben im Himmel bin, will ich auf dich herab sehen, pflanz ein Bäumlein auf mein Grab, und wenn du etwas wünschest, schüttele dar- an, so sollst du es haben, und wenn du sonst in Noth bist, so will ich dir Hülfe schicken, nur bleib fromm und gut.“ Nachdem sie das gesagt, that sie die Augen zu und starb; das Kind aber weinte und pflanzte ein Bäumlein auf das Grab und brauchte kein Wasser hin zu tragen, und es zu begießen, denn es war ge- nug mit seinen Thränen.

Der Schnee deckte ein weiß Tüchlein auf der Mutter Grab, und als die Sonne es wie- der weggezogen hatte, und das Bäumlein zum zweitenmal grün geworden war, da nahm sich der Mann eine andere Frau. Die Stiefmut- ter aber hatte schon zwei Töchter, von ihrem ersten Mann, die waren von Angesicht schön, von Herzen aber stolz und hoffährtig und bös. Wie nun die Hochzeit gewesen, und alle drei in das Haus gefahren kamen, da ging schlim- me Zeit für das arme Kind an. „Was macht der garstige Unnütz in den Stuben, sagte die Stiefmutter, fort mit ihr in die Küche, wenn sie Brod essen will, muß sies erst verdient ha- ben, sie kann unsere Magd seyn.“ Da nah- men ihm die Stiefschwestern die Kleider weg, und zogen ihm einen alten grauen Rock an: „der ist gut für dich!“ sagten sie, lachten es aus und führten es in die Küche. Da mußte das arme Kind so schwere Arbeit thun: früh vor Tag aufstehen, Wasser tragen, Feuer an- machen, kochen und waschen und die Stief- schwestern thaten ihm noch alles gebrannte Her- zeleid an, spotteten es, schütteten ihm Erbsen und Linsen in die Äche, da mußte es den gan- zen Tag sitzen und sie wieder auslesen. Wenn es müd war Abends kam es in kein Bett, son- dern mußte sich neben dem Heerd in die Äche legen. Und weil es da immer in Äche und Staub herumwühlte und schmutzig aussah, ga- ben sie ihm den Namen Ächenputtel.

Auf eine Zeit stellte der König einen Ball an, der sollte in aller Pracht drei Tage dauern, und sein Sohn, der Prinz, sollte sich eine Ge- mahlin aussuchen; dazu wurden die zwei stol- zen Schwestern auch eingeladen. „Äschenput- tel riefen sie, komm herauf, kämme uns die Haare, bürst uns die Schuhe und schnalle sie fest, wir gehen auf den Ball zu dem Prinzen.“ Ächenputtel gab sich alle Mühe und putzte sie so gut es konnte, sie gaben ihm aber nur Scheltworte dazwischen, und als sie fertig wa- ren, fragten sie spöttisch: „Ächenputtel, du gingst wohl gern mit auf den Ball?“ „Ach ja, wie kann ich aber hingehen, ich habe keine Kleider.“ „Nein, sagte die älteste, das wär mir recht, daß du dich dort sehen ließest, wir müßten uns schämen, wenn die Leute hörten, daß du unsere Schwester wärest; du gehörst in die Küche, da hast du eine Schüssel voll Linsen, wann wir wieder kommen muß sie gelesen seyn, und hüt dich, daß keine böse darunter ist, sonst hast du nichts Gutes zu erwarten.“

Damit gingen sie fort, und Ächenputtel stand und sah ihnen nach, und als es nichts mehr sehen konnte, ging es traurig in die Kü- che, und schüttete die Linsen auf den Heerd, da war es ein großer, großer Haufen. „Ach, sagte es und seufzte dabei, da muß ich dran lesen bis Mitternacht und darf die Augen nicht zufallen lassen, und wenn sie mir noch so weh thun, wenn das meine Mutter wüßte!“ Da kniete es sich vor den Heerd in die Äche und wollte anfangen zu lesen, indem flogen zwei weiße Tauben durchs Fenster und setzten sich neben die Linsen auf den Heerd; sie nickten mit den Köpfchen und sagten: „Ächenputtel, sollen wir dir helfen Linsen lesen? „Ja, ant- wortete Ächenputtel: die schlechten ins Kröpfchen, die guten ins Töpfchen.“ Und pick, pick! pick, pick! fingen sie an und fraßen die schlechten weg und ließen die guten liegen. Und in einer Viertelstunde waren die Linsen so rein, daß auch nicht eine falsche dar- unter war, und Ächenputtel konnte sie alle ins Töpfchen streichen. Darauf aber sagten die Tauben: „Ächenputtel, willst du deine Schwe- stern mit dem Prinzen tanzen sehen, so steig auf den Taubenschlag.“ Ächenputtel ging ih- nen nach und stieg bis auf den letzten Leiter- sproß, da konnte es in den Saal sehen, und sah seine Schwestern mit dem Prinzen tanzen, und es flimmerte und glänzte von viel tausend Lichtern vor seinen Augen. Und als es sich satt gesehen, stieg es wieder herab, und es war ihm schwer ums Herz, und legte sich in die Äche und schlief ein.

Am andern Morgen kamen die zwei Schwe- stern in die Küche, und als sie sahen, daß Ächenputtel die Linsen rein gelesen, waren sie böse, denn sie wollten es gern schelten, und da sie das nicht konnten, huben sie an von dem Ball zu erzählen und sagten: „Ächenputtel, das ist eine Lust gewesen, bei dem Tanz, der Prinz, der allerschönste auf der Welt hat uns dazu geführt, und eine von uns wird seine Ge- mahlin werden.“ „Ja, sagte Ächenputtel, ich habe die Lichter flimmern sehen, das mag recht prächtig gewesen seyn.“ „Ei! wie hast du das angefangen,“ fragte die älteste. „Ich hab' oben auf den Taubenstall gestan- den.“ Wie sie das hörte, trieb sie der Neid und sie befahl, daß der Taubenstall gleich sollte niedergerissen werden.

Ächenputtel aber mußte sie wieder käm- men und putzen; da sagte die jüngste, die noch ein wenig Mitleid im Herzen hatte: „Ächen- puttel, wenns dunkel ist, kannst du hinzugehen und von außen durch die Fenster gucken!“ „Nein, sagte die älteste, das macht sie nur faul, da hast du einen Sack voll Wicken, Ächenputtel, da lese die guten und bösen aus- einander und sey fleißig, und wenn du sie mor- gen nicht rein hast, so schütte ich dir sie in die Äche und du mußt hungern, bis du sie alle herausgesucht hast.“

Ächenputtel setzte sich betrübt auf den Heerd und schüttete die Wicken aus. Da flogen die Tauben wieder herein und thaten freund- lich: „Ächenputtel, sollen wir dir die Wicken lesen?“ „Ja, die schlechten ins Kröpfchen, die guten ins Töpfchen.“ Pick, pick! pick, pick! gings so geschwind, als wären zwölf Hände da. Und als sie fertig wa- ren, sagten die Tauben: „Ächenputtel, willst du auch auf den Ball gehen und tanzen.“ „O du mein Gott, sagte es, wie kann ich in meinen schmutzigen Kleidern hingehen?“ „Geh zu dem Bäumlein auf deiner Mutter Grab, schüttele daran und wünsche dir schöne Kleider, komm aber vor Mitternacht wieder.“ da ging Ächenputtel hinaus, schüttelte das Bäumlein und sprach: „Bäumlein rüttel und schüttel dich, wirf schöne Kleider herab für mich!“ Kaum hatte da ging es das ausgesagt, da lag ein präch- tig silbern Kleid vor da ging ihm, Perlen, seidene Strümpfe mit silbernen Zwickeln und silberne Pantoffel und was sonst dazu gehörte. da ging Ächen- puttel trug alles nach Haus, und als da ging es sich gewaschen und angezogen hatte, da war es so schön wie eine Rose, die der Thau gewaschen hat. Und wie es vor die Hausthüre kam, so stand da ein Wagen mit sechs federgeschmück- ten Rappen und Bediente dabei in Blau und Silber, die hoben es hinein, und so gings im Gallop zu dem Schloß des Königs.

Der Prinz aber sah den Wagen vor dem Thor halten, und meinte eine fremde Prinzes- sin käme angefahren. Da ging er selbst die Treppe hinab, hob Ächenputtel hinaus und führte es in den Saal. Und als da der Glanz der viel tausend Lichter auf es fiel, da war es so schön, daß jedermann sich darüber verwun- derte, und die Schwestern standen auch da und ärgerten sich, daß jemand schöner war wie sie, aber sie dachten nimmermehr, daß das Ächen- puttel wäre, das zu Haus in der Äche lag. Der Prinz aber tanzte mit Ächenputtel und ward ihm königliche Ehre angethan. Er ge- dachte auch bei sich: ich soll mir eine Braut aussuchen, da weiß ich mir keine als diese. Für so lange Zeit in Äche und Traurigkeit lebte Ächenputtel nun in Pracht und Freude; als aber Mitternacht kam, eh' es zwölf geschla- gen, stand es auf, neigte sich und wie der Prinz bat und bat, so wollte es nicht länger bleiben. Da führte es der Prinz hinab, unten stand der Wagen und wartete, und so fuhr es fort in Pracht wie es gekommen war.

Als Ächenputtel zu Haus war, ging es wieder zu dem Bäumlein auf der Mutter Grab: „Bäumlein rüttel dich und schüttel dich! nimm die Kleider wieder für dich!“ damit ging es zurück, machte sich das Gesicht staubig und legte sich in die Äsche schlafen.

Am Morgen darauf kamen die Schwe- stern, sahen verdrießlich aus und schwiegen still. Ächenputtel sagte: „ihr habt wohl gestern Abend viel Freude gehabt“ „Nein, es war eine Prinzessin da, mit der hat der Prinz fast immer getanzt, es hat sie aber niemand ge- kannt und niemand gewußt, woher sie gekom- men ist. „Ist es vielleicht die gewesen, die in den prächtigen Wagen mit den sechs Rap- pen gefahren ist?“ sagte Ächenputtel. „Wo- her weißt du das?“ Ich stand in der Haus- thüre, da sah ich sie vorbeifahren.“ „In Zukunft bleib bei deiner Arbeit, sagte die älte- ste und sah Ächenputtel böse an, was brauchst du in der Hausthüre zu stehen.“

Ächenputtel mußte zum drittenmal die zwei Schwestern putzen, und zum Lohn gaben sie ihm eine Schüssel mit Erbsen, die sollte sie rein lesen; „und daß du dich nicht unterstehst von der Arbeit wegzugehen, rief die älteste noch nach. Ächenputtel gedachte: wenn nur meine Tauben nicht ausbleiben, und das Herz schlug ihm ein wenig. Die Tauben aber ka- wie an dem vorigen Abend und sagten: „Ächenputtel, sollen wir dir die Erbsen le- sen?“ „Ja, die schlechten ins Kröpfchen, die guten ins Töpfchen.“ Die Tauben pickten wieder die bösen heraus, und waren bald damit fertig, dann sagten sie: „Ächenputtel, schüttele das Bäumlein, das wird dir noch schönere Kleider herunter werfen, geh auf den Ball, aber hüte dich, daß du vor Mitternacht wieder kommst.“ Ächenputtel ging hin: „Bäumlein rüttel dich und schüttel dich, wirf schöne Kleider herab für mich.“ Da fiel ein Kleid herab noch viel herrlicher und prächtiger als das vorige, ganz von Gold und Edelgesteinen, dabei goldgezwickelte Strümpfe und goldene Pantoffel; und als Ächenputtel damit angekleidet war, da glänzte es recht, wie die Sonne am Mittag. Vor der Thüre hielt ein Wagen mit sechs Schimmeln, die hatten hohe weiße Federbüsche auf dem Kopf, und die Bedienten waren in Roth und Gold gekleidet. Als Ächenputtel ankam, stand schon der Prinz auf der Treppe und führte sie in den Saal. Und waren gestern alle über ihre Schönheit er- staunt, so erstaunten sie heute noch mehr und die Schwestern standen in der Ecke und waren blaß vor Neid, und hätten sie gewußt, daß das Ächenputtel war, das zu Haus in der Äsche lag, sie wären gestorben vor Neid.

Der Prinz aber wollte wissen, wer die fremde Prinzessin sey, woher sie gekommen und wohin sie fahre, und hatte Leute auf die Stra- ße gestellt, die sollten Acht darauf haben, und damit sie nicht so schnell fortlaufen könne, hat- te er die Treppe ganz mit Pech bestreichen las- sen. Ächenputtel tanzte und tanzte mit dem Prinzen, war in Freuden und gedachte nicht an Mitternacht. Auf einmal, wie es mitten im Tanzen war, hörte es den Glockenschlag, da fiel ihm ein, wie die Tauben es gewarnt, erschrack und eilte zur Thüre hinaus und flog recht die Treppe hinunter. Weil die aber mit Pech bestrichen war, blieb einer von den golde- nen Pantoffeln festhängen, und in der Angst dacht es nicht daran, ihn mitzunehmen. Und wie es den letzten Schritt von der Treppe that, da hatt' es zwölf ausgeschlagen, da war Wa- gen und Pferde verschwunden und Ächenput- tel stand in seinen Äschenkleidern auf der dun- keln Straße. Der Prinz war ihm nachgeeilt, auf der Treppe fand er den goldenen Pantof- fel, riß ihn los und hob ihn auf, wie er aber unten hinkam, war alles verschwunden; die Leute auch, die zur Wache ausgestellt wa- ren, kamen und sagten, daß sie nichts gesehen hätten.

Ächenputtel war froh, daß es nicht schlim- mer gekommen war, und ging nach Haus, da steckte es sein trübes Oel-Lämpchen an, hängte es in den Schornstein und legte sich in die Äsche. Es währte nicht lange, so kamen die beiden Schwestern auch und riefen: „Ächen- puttel, steh auf und leucht uns.“ Ächenput- tel gähnte und that als wacht es aus dem Schlaf. Bei dem Leuchten aber hörte es, wie die eine sagte: „Gott weiß, wer die verwünsch- te Prinzessin ist, daß sie in der Erde begraben läg! der Prinz hat nur mit ihr getanzt und als sie weg war, hat er gar nicht mehr blei- ben wollen und das ganze Fest hat ein Ende gehabt.“ „Es war recht, als wären alle Lichter auf einmal ausgeblasen worden,“ sagte die andere. Ächenputtel wußte wohl wer die fremde Prinzessin war, aber es sagte kein Wörtchen.

Der Prinz aber gedachte, ist dir alles an- dere fehlgeschlagen, so wird dir der Pantoffel die Braut finden helfen, und ließ bekannt ma- chen, welcher der goldene Pantoffel passe, die solle seine Gemahlin werden. Aber allen war er viel zu klein, ja manche hätten ihren Fuß nicht hineingebracht, und wären die zwei Pan- toffel ein einziger gewesen. Endlich kam die Reihe auch an die beiden Schwestern, die Pro- be zu machen; sie waren froh, denn sie hatten kleine schöne Füße und glaubten, uns kann es nicht fehlschlagen, wär der Prinz nur gleich zu uns gekommen. „Hört, sagte die Mutter heim- lich, da habt ihr ein Messer, und wenn euch der Pantoffel doch noch zu eng ist, so schnei- det euch ein Stück vom Fuß ab, es thut ein bischen weh, was schadet das aber, es vergeht bald und eine von euch wird Königin.“ Da ging die älteste in ihre Kammer und probirte den Pantoffel an, die Fußspitze kam hinein, aber die Ferse war zu groß, da nahm sie das Messer und schnitt sich ein Stück von der Fer- se, bis sie den Fuß in den Pantoffel hinein- zwängte. So ging sie heraus zu dem Prin- zen, und wie der sah, daß sie den Pantoffel anhatte, sagte er, das sey die Braut, führte sie zum Wagen und wollte mit ihr fortfahren. Wie er aber ans Thor kam, saßen oben die Tauben und riefen: „Rucke di guck, rucke di guck! Blut ist im Schuck: (Schuh) Der Schuck ist zu klein, Die rechte Braut sitzt noch daheim!“ Der Prinz bückte sich und sah auf den Pan- toffel, da quoll das Blut heraus, und da merk- te er, daß er betrogen war, und führte die fal- sche Braut zurück. Die Mutter aber sagte zur zweiten Tochter: „nimm du den Pantoffel, und wenn er dir zu kurz ist, so schneide lieber vor- ne an den Zehen ab. Da nahm sie den Pan- toffel in ihre Kammer, und als der Fuß zu groß war, da biß sie die Zähne zusammen und schnitt ein groß Stück von den Zehen ab, und drückte den Pantoffel geschwind an. Wie sie damit hervortrat, meinte er, das wäre die rech- te und wollte mit ihr fortfahren. Als er aber in das Thor kam, riefen die Tauben wieder: „Rucke di guck, rucke di guck! Blut ist im Schuck: Der Schuck ist zu klein, Die rechte Braut sitzt noch daheim!“ Der Prinz sah nieder, da waren die weißen Strümpfe der Braut roth gefärbt und das Blut war hoch herauf gedrungen. Da brachte sie der Prinz der Mutter wieder und sagte: „das ist auch nicht die rechte Braut; aber ist nicht noch eine Tochter im Haus.“ „Nein, sagte die Mutter, nur ein garstiges Ächenput- tel ist noch da, das sitzt unten in der Äsche, dem kann der Pantoffel nicht passen. Sie wollte es auch nicht rufen lassen, bis es der Prinz durchaus verlangte. Da ward Ächen- puttel gerufen und wie es hörte, daß der Prinz da sey, wusch es sich geschwind Gesicht und Hände frisch und rein; und wie es in die Stube trat, neigte es sich, der Prinz aber reichte ihr den goldenen Pantoffel und sagte: „probier ihn an! und wenn er dir paßt, wirst du meine Gemahlin.“ Da streift es den schwe- ren Schuh von dem linken Fuß ab, setzt ihn auf den goldenen Pantoffel und drückte ein klein wenig, da stand es darin, als wär er ihm an- gegossen. Und als es sich aufbückte, sah ihm der Prinz ins Gesicht, da erkannte er die schö- ne Prinzessin wieder und rief: „das ist die rechte Braut.“ Die Stiefmutter und die zwei stolzen Schwestern erschracken und wurden bleich, aber der Prinz führte Ächenputtel fort und hob es in den Wagen, und als sie durchs Thor fuhren, da riefen die Tauben:

„Rucke di guck, rucke di guck! Kein Blut im Schuck: Der Schuck ist nicht zu klein, Die rechte Braut, die führt er heim!“

A rich man's wife became sick, and when she felt that her end was drawing near, she called her only daughter to her bedside and said, "Dear child, remain pious and good, and then our dear God will always protect you, and I will look down on you from heaven and be near you." With this she closed her eyes and died.

The girl went out to her mother's grave every day and wept, and she remained pious and good. When winter came the snow spread a white cloth over the grave, and when the spring sun had removed it again, the man took himself another wife.

This wife brought two daughters into the house with her. They were beautiful, with fair faces, but evil and dark hearts. Times soon grew very bad for the poor stepchild.

"Why should that stupid goose sit in the parlor with us?" they said. "If she wants to eat bread, then she will have to earn it. Out with this kitchen maid!"

They took her beautiful clothes away from her, dressed her in an old gray smock, and gave her wooden shoes. "Just look at the proud princess! How decked out she is!" they shouted and laughed as they led her into the kitchen.

There she had to do hard work from morning until evening, get up before daybreak, carry water, make the fires, cook, and wash. Besides this, the sisters did everything imaginable to hurt her. They made fun of her, scattered peas and lentils into the ashes for her, so that she had to sit and pick them out again. In the evening when she had worked herself weary, there was no bed for her. Instead she had to sleep by the hearth in the ashes. And because she always looked dusty and dirty, they called her Cinderella.

One day it happened that the father was going to the fair, and he asked his two stepdaughters what he should bring back for them.

"Beautiful dresses," said the one.

"Pearls and jewels," said the other.

"And you, Cinderella," he said, "what do you want?"

"Father, break off for me the first twig that brushes against your hat on your way home."

So he bought beautiful dresses, pearls, and jewels for his two stepdaughters. On his way home, as he was riding through a green thicket, a hazel twig brushed against him and knocked off his hat. Then he broke off the twig and took it with him.Arriving home, he gave his stepdaughters the things that they had asked for, and he gave Cinderella the twig from the hazel bush.

Cinderella thanked him, went to her mother's grave, and planted the branch on it, and she wept so much that her tears fell upon it and watered it. It grew and became a beautiful tree.

Cinderella went to this tree three times every day, and beneath it she wept and prayed. A white bird came to the tree every time, and whenever she expressed a wish, the bird would throw down to her what she had wished for.

Now it happened that the king proclaimed a festival that was to last three days. All the beautiful young girls in the land were invited, so that his son could select a bride for himself. When the two stepsisters heard that they too had been invited, they were in high spirits.

They called Cinderella, saying, "Comb our hair for us. Brush our shoes and fasten our buckles. We are going to the festival at the king's castle."

Cinderella obeyed, but wept, because she too would have liked to go to the dance with them. She begged her stepmother to allow her to go.

"You, Cinderella?" she said. "You, all covered with dust and dirt, and you want to go to the festival?. You have neither clothes nor shoes, and yet you want to dance!"

However, because Cinderella kept asking, the stepmother finally said, "I have scattered a bowl of lentils into the ashes for you. If you can pick them out again in two hours, then you may go with us."

The girl went through the back door into the garden, and called out, "You tame pigeons, you turtledoves, and all you birds beneath the sky, come and help me to gather:

The good ones go into the pot, The bad ones go into your crop."

Two white pigeons came in through the kitchen window, and then the turtledoves, and finally all the birds beneath the sky came whirring and swarming in, and lit around the ashes. The pigeons nodded their heads and began to pick, pick, pick, pick. And the others also began to pick, pick, pick, pick. They gathered all the good grains into the bowl. Hardly one hour had passed before they were finished, and they all flew out again.

The girl took the bowl to her stepmother, and was happy, thinking that now she would be allowed to go to the festival with them.

But the stepmother said,"No, Cinderella, you have no clothes, and you don't know how to dance. Everyone would only laugh at you."

Cinderella began to cry, and then the stepmother said, "You may go if you are able to pick two bowls of lentils out of the ashes for me in one hour," thinking to herself, "She will never be able to do that."

The girl went through the back door into the garden, and called out, "You tame pigeons, you turtledoves, and all you birds beneath the sky, come and help me to gather:

The good ones go into the pot, The bad ones go into your crop."

Two white pigeons came in through the kitchen window, and then the turtledoves, and finally all the birds beneath the sky came whirring and swarming in, and lit around the ashes. The pigeons nodded their heads and began to pick, pick, pick, pick. And the others also began to pick, pick, pick, pick. They gathered all the good grains into the bowls. Before a half hour had passed they were finished, and they all flew out again.

The girl took the bowls to her stepmother, and was happy, thinking that now she would be allowed to go to the festival with them.

But the stepmother said,"It's no use. You are not coming with us, for you have no clothes, and you don't know how to dance. We would be ashamed of you." With this she turned her back on Cinderella, and hurried away with her two proud daughters.

Now that no one else was at home, Cinderella went to her mother's grave beneath the hazel tree, and cried out:

Shake and quiver, little tree, Throw gold and silver down to me.

Then the bird threw a gold and silver dress down to her, and slippers embroidered with silk and silver. She quickly put on the dress and went to the festival.

Her stepsisters and her stepmother did not recognize her. They thought she must be a foreign princess, for she looked so beautiful in the golden dress. They never once thought it was Cinderella, for they thought that she was sitting at home in the dirt, looking for lentils in the ashes.

The prince approached her, took her by the hand, and danced with her. Furthermore, he would dance with no one else. He never let go of her hand, and whenever anyone else came and asked her to dance, he would say, "She is my dance partner."

She danced until evening, and then she wanted to go home. But the prince said, "I will go along and escort you," for he wanted to see to whom the beautiful girl belonged. However, she eluded him and jumped into the pigeon coop. The prince waited until her father came, and then he told him that the unknown girl had jumped into the pigeon coop.

The old man thought, "Could it be Cinderella?"

He had them bring him an ax and a pick so that he could break the pigeon coop apart, but no one was inside.When they got home Cinderella was lying in the ashes, dressed in her dirty clothes. A dim little oil-lamp was burning in the fireplace. Cinderella had quickly jumped down from the back of the pigeon coop and had run to the hazel tree. There she had taken off her beautiful clothes and laid them on the grave, and the bird had taken them away again. Then, dressed in her gray smock, she had returned to the ashes in the kitchen.

The next day when the festival began anew, and her parents and her stepsisters had gone again, Cinderella went to the hazel tree and said:

Shake and quiver, little tree, Throw gold and silver down to me.

Then the bird threw down an even more magnificent dress than on the preceding day. When Cinderella appeared at the festival in this dress, everyone was astonished at her beauty. The prince had waited until she came, then immediately took her by the hand, and danced only with her. When others came and asked her to dance with them, he said, "She is my dance partner."

When evening came she wanted to leave, and the prince followed her, wanting to see into which house she went. But she ran away from him and into the garden behind the house. A beautiful tall tree stood there, on which hung the most magnificent pears. She climbed as nimbly as a squirrel into the branches, and the prince did not know where she had gone. He waited until her father came, then said to him, "The unknown girl has eluded me, and I believe she has climbed up the pear tree.

The father thought,"Could it be Cinderella?" He had an ax brought to him and cut down the tree, but no one was in it. When they came to the kitchen, Cinderella was lying there in the ashes as usual, for she had jumped down from the other side of the tree, had taken the beautiful dress back to the bird in the hazel tree, and had put on her gray smock.

On the third day, when her parents and sisters had gone away, Cinderella went again to her mother's grave and said to the tree:

Shake and quiver, little tree, Throw gold and silver down to me.

This time the bird threw down to her a dress that was more splendid and magnificent than any she had yet had, and the slippers were of pure gold. When she arrived at the festival in this dress, everyone was so astonished that they did not know what to say. The prince danced only with her, and whenever anyone else asked her to dance, he would say, "She is my dance partner."

When evening came Cinderella wanted to leave, and the prince tried to escort her, but she ran away from him so quickly that he could not follow her. The prince, however, had set a trap. He had had the entire stairway smeared with pitch. When she ran down the stairs, her left slipper stuck in the pitch. The prince picked it up. It was small and dainty, and of pure gold.

The next morning, he went with it to the man, and said to him, No one shall be my wife except for the one whose foot fits this golden shoe."

The two sisters were happy to hear this, for they had pretty feet. With her mother standing by, the older one took the shoe into her bedroom to try it on. She could not get her big toe into it, for the shoe was too small for her. Then her mother gave her a knife and said, "Cut off your toe. When you are queen you will no longer have to go on foot."

The girl cut off her toe, forced her foot into the shoe, swallowed the pain, and went out to the prince. He took her on his horse as his bride and rode away with her. However, they had to ride past the grave, and there, on the hazel tree, sat the two pigeons, crying out:

Rook di goo, rook di goo! There's blood in the shoe. The shoe is too tight, This bride is not right!

Then he looked at her foot and saw how the blood was running from it. He turned his horse around and took the false bride home again, saying that she was not the right one, and that the other sister should try on the shoe. She went into her bedroom, and got her toes into the shoe all right, but her heel was too large.

Then her mother gave her a knife, and said, "Cut a piece off your heel. When you are queen you will no longer have to go on foot."

The girl cut a piece off her heel, forced her foot into the shoe, swallowed the pain, and went out to the prince. He took her on his horse as his bride and rode away with her. When they passed the hazel tree, the two pigeons were sitting in it, and they cried out:

Rook di goo, rook di goo! There's blood in the shoe. The shoe is too tight, This bride is not right!

He looked down at her foot and saw how the blood was running out of her shoe, and how it had stained her white stocking all red. Then he turned his horse around and took the false bride home again.

This is not the right one, either," he said. "Don't you have another daughter?"

"No," said the man. "There is only a deformed little Cinderella from my first wife, but she cannot possibly be the bride."

The prince told him to send her to him, but the mother answered, "Oh, no, she is much too dirty. She cannot be seen."

But the prince insisted on it, and they had to call Cinderella. She first washed her hands and face clean, and then went and bowed down before the prince, who gave her the golden shoe. She sat down on a stool, pulled her foot out of the heavy wooden shoe, and put it into the slipper, and it fitted her perfectly.

When she stood up the prince looked into her face, and he recognized the beautiful girl who had danced with him. He cried out, "She is my true bride."

The stepmother and the two sisters were horrified and turned pale with anger. The prince, however, took Cinderella onto his horse and rode away with her. As they passed by the hazel tree, the two white pigeons cried out:

Rook di goo, rook di goo! No blood's in the shoe. The shoe's not too tight, This bride is right!

After they had cried this out, they both flew down and lit on Cinderella's shoulders, one on the right, the other on the left, and remained sitting there.

When the wedding with the prince was to be held, the two false sisters came, wanting to gain favor with Cinderella and to share her good fortune. When the bridal couple walked into the church, the older sister walked on their right side and the younger on their left side, and the pigeons pecked out one eye from each of them. Afterwards, as they came out of the church, the older one was on the left side, and the younger one on the right side, and then the pigeons pecked out the other eye from each of them. And thus, for their wickedness and falsehood, they were punished with blindness as long as they lived.

conclusions

main conclusion

Women in translation is a well versed and forever applicable to society. This project is proof of concept on how women are percieved, not only through the eyes of the Grimms' brothers, but in the world today. The translation for English to German is immensely different in how it is written. There is much less dialogue than the English translation. The perceptions of positive, neutral, and negative conversations differ between characters from one story to the next. Some of these differences could be due to various ways of completing markup, but for example, the German version of Little Snow White seems to be simplified compared to the English version. There only seems to be one queen in the tale, but the English version includes a second. It is possible the the English versions may give additional background, but then clearly the translation is also an adapted version.

The types of women characters, generally, are as follows:

Birth mothers, who are generally loving towards there children

Stepmothers, who tend to be loving towards there own children, but "evil" towards their stepchildren

Witches, who tend to come across as nuturing towards young children, but do so to manipulate them

Daughters, who tend to be caring and driven in their tasks

Stepdaughters, who tend to be rude to the step siblings, spoiled, and lazy

Overall, the mothers and daughters seem to be "good", while the stepmothers, stepdaughters, and witches seem to be "evil".

other considerations

This project is a create way to continue our research and continue to develop digital humanity skills. As a group, if we were to start this again and had much more time, we would have more carefully deciphered our xml markup. It is clear to us now that this markup rules our results. We would have read through the the tales more delibrately, matched our references for characters and other elements, as well as breaking up tasks to further focus our analysis on acts or dialogue. With the possible continuation of this project, it is possible for us to dive deeper in both the acts and dialogue.

corpus

As a team, we chose ten Grimms’ Fairy Tales to explore that we thought had interesting initial characteristics regarding how women are portrayed in the tales. Of our four team members, the English texts were divided amongst three of us for markup, while the German was handled by one. The markup for each tale was informed by the individual interpretation of the team member charged with its analysis. This ultimately resulted in inconsistencies in the resulting data.

Our tales can be found in the menu above. You can click on any of them and it will take you to a new page where you will see two versions of the story that you chose. One story will be in German and one will be in English. We wanted to show the difference in hostile, benevolent, and neutral interactions when they have to do with the women in the stories.

When looking at the texts you will see colors:

Hostile is red.

Benevolent is indigo.

Neutral is green.

Feel free to browse and see how if you can find any differences!

Frau Holle

English Version

German Version

A widow had two daughters, the one was beautiful and industrious, the other ugly and lazy. She greatly favored the ugly, lazy girl, because she was her own daughter. And the other one had to do all the work, and be the Cinderella of the house.

Every day the poor girl had to sit by a well, next to the highway, and spin so much that her fingers bled. Now it happened that one day the reel was completely bloody, so she dipped it in the well, to wash it off, but it dropped out of her hand and fell in. She cried, ran to her stepmother, and told her of the mishap. She scolded her so sharply, and was so merciless that she said, "Since you have let the reel fall in, you must fetch it out again."

Then the girl went back to the well, and did not know what to do. Terrified, she jumped into the well to get the reel. She lost her senses.And when she awoke and came to herself again, she was in a beautiful meadow where the sun was shining, and there were many thousands of flowers. She walked across this meadow and came to an oven full of bread. The bread called out, "Oh, take me out. Take me out, or I'll burn. I've been thoroughly baked for a long time." So she stepped up to it, and with a baker's peel took everything out, one loaf after the other.

After that she walked further and came to a tree laden with apples. "Shake me. Shake me. We apples are all ripe." cried the tree. So she shook the tree until the apples fell as though it were raining apples. When none were left in the tree, she gathered them into a pile, and then continued on her way.

Finally she came to a small house. An old woman was peering out from inside. She had very large teeth, which frightened the girl, and she wanted to run away. But the old woman called out to her,"Don't be afraid, dear child. Stay here with me, and if you do my housework in an orderly fashion, it will go well with you. Only you must take care to make my bed well and shake it diligently until the feathers fly, then it will snow in the world.* I am Frau Holle."

Because the old woman spoke so kindly to her, the girl took heart, agreed, and started in her service. The girl took care of everything to Frau Holle's satisfaction and always shook her featherbed vigorously until the feathers flew about like snowflakes. Therefore she had a good life with her: no angry words, and boiled or roast meat every day.

Now after she had been with Frau Holle for a time, she became sad. At first she did not know what was the matter with her, but at last she determined that it was homesickness. Even though she was many thousands of times better off here than at home, still she had a yearning to return. Finally she said to the old woman, "I have such a longing for home, and even though I am very well off here, I cannot stay longer. I must go up again to my own people."

Frau Holle said, "I am pleased that you long for your home again, and because you have served me so faithfully, I will take you back myself." With that she took her by the hand and led her to a large gate.

The gate was opened, and while the girl was standing under it, an immense rain of gold fell, and all the gold stuck to her, so that she was completely covered with it. 'This is yours because you have been so industrious," said Frau Holle, and at the same time she gave her back the reel which had fallen into the well.

With that the gate was closed and the girl found herself above on earth, not far from her mother's house. And as she entered the yard the rooster, sitting on the well, cried:

Cock-a-doodle-doo, Our golden girl is here anew.

Then she went inside to her mother, and as she arrived all covered with gold, she was well received, both by her mother and her sister. The girl told all that had happened to her, and when the mother heard how she had come to the great wealth, she wanted to achieve the same fortune for the other, the ugly and lazy daughter. She made her go and sit by the well and spin. And to make her reel bloody, the lazy girl pricked her fingers and shoved her hand into a thorn bush. Then she threw the reel into the well, and jumped in herself.

Like the other girl, she too came to the beautiful meadow and walked along the same path. When she came to the oven, the bread cried again, "Oh, take me out. Take me out, or else I'll burn. I've been thoroughly baked for a long time."

But the lazy girl answered, "As if I would want to get all dirty," and walked away.

Soon she came to the apple tree. It cried out, "Oh, shake me. Shake me. We apples are all ripe."

But she answered, "Oh yes, one could fall on my head," and with that she walked on.

When she came to Frau Holle's house, she was not afraid, because she had already heard about her large teeth, and she immediately began to work for her. On the first day she forced herself, was industrious, and obeyed Frau Holle, when she said something to her, because she was thinking about all the gold that she would give her. But on the second day she already began to be lazy, on the third day even more so, and then she didn't even want to get up in the morning. She did not make the bed for Frau Holle, the way she was supposed to, and she did not shake it until the feathers flew. Frau Holle soon became tired of this and dismissed her of her duties. This was just what the lazy girl wanted, for she thought that she would now get the rain of gold.

Frau Holle led her too to the gate. She stood beneath it, but instead of gold, a large kettle full of pitch spilled over her. "That is the reward for your services," said Frau Holle, and closed the gate.

Then the lazy girl went home, entirely covered with pitch. As soon as the rooster on the well saw her, he cried out:

Cock-a-doodle-doo, Our dirty girl is here anew.

And the pitch stuck fast to her, and did not come off as long as she lived.

Eine Wittwe hatte zwei Töchter, davon war die eine schön und fleißig, die andere häß- lich und faul. Sie hatte aber die häßliche und faule viel lieber, und die andere mußte alle Ar- beit thun und war recht der Aschenputtel im Haus. Einmal war das Mädchen hingegan- gen, Wasser zu holen, und wie es sich bückte den Eimer aus dem Brunnen zu ziehen, bückte es sich zu tief und fiel hinein. Und als es er- wachte und wieder zu sich selber kam, war es auf einer schönen Wiese, da schien die Sonne und waren viel tausend Blumen. Auf der Wiese gieng es fort und kam zu einem Back- ofen, der war voller Brot; das Brot aber rief: „ach! zieh mich 'raus, zieh mich 'raus, sonst verbrenn' ich, ich bin schon längst ausgebacken!“ da trat es fleißig herzu und holte alles heraus. Darnach ging es weiter und kam zu einem Baum, der hing voll Aepfel und rief ihm zu: „ach! schüttel mich! schüttel mich! wir Aepfel sind allemiteinander reif!“ Da schüttelt' es den Baum, daß die Aepfel fielen, als regenten sie, solang bis keiner mehr oben war, darnach ging es wieder fort. Endlich kam es zu einem klei- nen Haus, daraus guckte eine alte Frau, weil sie aber so große Zähne hatte, ward ihm Angst und es wollte fortlaufen. Die alte Frau aber rief ihm nach: „fürcht dich nicht, liebes Kind, bleib bei mir, wenn du alle Arbeit im Haus ordentlich thun willst, so soll dirs gut gehn: nur mußt du recht darauf Acht geben daß du mein Bett gut machst, und es fleißig aufschüt- telst, daß die Federn fliegen, dann schneit es in der Welt; Darum sagt man in Hessen, wenn es schneit: die Frau Holle macht ihr Bett. Ich bin die Frau Holle.“ Weil die Alte so gut sprach, willigte das Mädchen ein und begab sich in ihren Dienst. Es besorgte auch alles nach ihrer Zufriedenheit und schüt- telte ihr das Bett immer gewaltig auf, dafür hatte es auch ein gut Leben bei ihr, kein böses Wort und alle Tage Gesottenes und Gebrate- nes. Nun war es eine Zeitlang bei der Frau Holle, da ward es traurig in seinem Herzen und ob es hier gleich viel tausendmal besser war, als zu Haus, so hatte es doch ein Ver- langen dahin; endlich sagte es zu ihr: „ich habe den Jammer nach Haus kriegt, und wenn es mir auch noch so gut hier geht, so kann ich doch nicht länger bleiben.“ Die Frau Holle sagte: „du hast Recht und weil du mir so treu gedient hast, so will ich dich selbst wieder hin- aufbringen.“ Sie nahm es darauf bei der Hand und führte es vor ein großes Thor. Das ward aufgethan und wie das Mädchen darun- ter stand, fiel ein gewaltiger Goldregen, und alles Gold blieb an ihm hängen, so daß es über und über davon bedeckt war. „Das sollst du haben, weil du so fleißig gewesen bist,“ sprach die Frau Holle. Darauf ward das Thor verschlossen und es war oben auf der Welt, da ging es heim zu seiner Mutter und weil es so mit Gold bedeckt ankam, ward es gut aufge- nommen.

Als die Mutter hörte, wie es zu dem Reich- thum gekommen, wollte sie der andern schönen und faulen Tochter gern dasselbe Glück verschaf- fen, und sie mußte sich auch in den Brunnen stürzen. Sie erwachte, wie die andere auf der schönen Wiese und ging auf demselben Pfad weiter. Als sie zu dem Backofen gelangte, schrie das Brod wieder: „ach! zieh mich 'raus, zieh mich 'raus, sonst verbrenn ich, ich bin schon längst ausgebacken!“ die Faule aber antworte- te: „da hätt' ich Lust, mich schmutzig zu ma- chen!“ und ging fort. Bald kam sie zu dem Apfelbaum, der rief: „ach! schüttel mich! schüt- tel mich! wir Aepfel sind alle mit einander reif“ sie antwortete aber: „du kommst mir recht, es könnt mir einer auf den Kopf fallen!“ ging damit weiter. Als sie vor der Frau Holle Haus kam, fürchtete sie sich nicht, weil sie von ihren großen Zähnen schon gehört hatte, und verdingte sich gleich zu ihr. Am ersten Tag that sie sich Gewalt an und war fleißig und folgte der Frau Holle, wenn sie ihr etwas sagte, denn sie gedachte an das viele Gold, daß sie ihr schenken würde; am zweiten Tag aber fing sie schon an zu faullenzen, am dritten noch mehr, da wollte sie Morgens gar nicht aufstehen, sie machte auch der Frau Holle das Bett schlecht und schüttelte es nicht recht, daß die Federn aufflogen. Das ward die Frau Holle bald müd und sagte der Faulen den Dienst auf. Die war es wohl zufrieden und meinte nun werde der Goldregen kommen, die Frau Holle führte sie auch hin zu dem Thor als sie aber darunter stand, ward statt des Golds ein großer Kessel voll Pech ausgeschüttet. „Das ist zur Beloh- nung deiner Dienste“ sagte die Frau Holle und schloß das Thor zu. Da kam die Faule heim, ganz mit Pech bedeckt, und das hat ihr Lebtag nicht wieder abgehen wollen.

Hansel and Gretel

English Version

German Version

Next to a great forest there lived a poor woodcutter with his wife and his two children. The boy's name was Hansel and the girl's name was Gretel. He had but little to eat, and once, when a great famine came to the land, he could no longer provide even their daily bread.

One evening as he was lying in bed worrying about his problems, he sighed and said to his wife, "What is to become of us? How can we feed our children when we have nothing for ourselves?"

"Man, do you know what?" answered the woman. "Early tomorrow morning we will take the two children out into the thickest part of the woods, make a fire for them, and give each of them a little piece of bread, then leave them by themselves and go off to our work. They will not find their way back home, and we will be rid of them."

"No, woman," said the man. "I will not do that. How could I bring myself to abandon my own children alone in the woods? Wild animals would soon come and tear them to pieces."

"Oh, you fool," she said, "then all four of us will starve. All you can do is to plane the boards for our coffins." And she gave him no peace until he agreed.

"But I do feel sorry for the poor children," said the man.

The two children had not been able to fall asleep because of their hunger, and they heard what the stepmother had said to the father.

Gretel cried bitter tears and said to Hansel, "It is over with us!"

"Be quiet, Gretel," said Hansel, "and don't worry. I know what to do."

And as soon as the adults had fallen asleep, he got up, pulled on his jacket, opened the lower door, and crept outside. The moon was shining brightly,and the white pebbles in front of the house were glistening like silver coins. Hansel bent over and filled his jacket pockets with them, as many as would fit

Then he went back into the house and said, "Don't worry, Gretel. Sleep well. God will not forsake us." Then he went back to bed.

At daybreak, even before sunrise, the woman came and woke the two children. Get up, you lazybones. We are going into the woods to fetch wood." Then she gave each one a little piece of bread, saying, "Here is something for midday. Don't eat it any sooner, for you'll not get any more."

Gretel put the bread under her apron, because Hansel's pockets were full of stones. Then all together they set forth into the woods. After they had walked a little way, Hansel began stopping again and again and looking back toward the house.

The father said, "Hansel, why are you stopping and looking back? Pay attention now, and don't forget your legs."

"Oh, father," said Hansel, "I am looking at my white cat that is sitting on the roof and wants to say good-bye to me."

The woman said, "You fool, that isn't your cat. That's the morning sun shining on the chimney."

However, Hansel had not been looking at his cat but instead had been dropping the shiny pebbles from his pocket onto the path.

When they arrived in the middle of the woods, the father said, "You children gather some wood, and I will make a fire so you won't freeze."

Hansel and Gretel gathered together some twigs, a pile as high as a small mountain

The twigs were set afire, and when the flames were burning well, the woman said, "Lie down by the fire and rest. We will go into the woods to cut wood. When we are finished, we will come back and get you."

Hansel and Gretel sat by the fire. When midday came each one ate his little piece of bread. Because they could hear the blows of an ax, they thought that the father was nearby. However, it was not an ax. It was a branch that he had tied to a dead tree and that the wind was beating back and forth. After they had sat there a long time, their eyes grew weary and closed, and they fell sound sleep.

When they finally awoke, it was dark at night. Gretel began to cry and said, "How will we get out of woods?" Hansel comforted her,"Wait a little until the moon comes up, and then we'll find the way."

After the full moon had come up, Hansel took his little sister by the hand. They followed the pebbles that glistened there like newly minted coins, showing them the way. They walked throughout the entire night, and as morning was breaking, they arrived at the father's house.

They knocked on the door, and when the woman opened it and saw that it was Hansel and Gretel, she said, "You wicked children, why did you sleep so long in the woods? We thought that you did not want to come back."

But the father was overjoyed when he saw his children once more, for he had not wanted to leave them alone.

Not long afterward there was once again great need everywhere, and one evening the children heard the mother say to the father, "We have again eaten up everything. We have only a half loaf of bread, and then the song will be over. We must get rid of the children. We will take them deeper into the woods, so they will not find their way out. Otherwise there will be no help for us."

The man was very disheartened,and he thought, "It would be better to share the last bit with the children."

But the woman would not listen to him, scolded him, and criticized him. He who says A must also say B, and because he had given in the first time, he had to do so the second time as well.

The children were still awake and had overheard the conversation. When the adults were asleep, Hansel got up again and wanted to gather pebbles as he had done before, but the woman had locked the door, and Hansel could not get out. But he comforted his little sister and said, "Don't cry, Gretel. Sleep well. God will help us."

Early the next morning the woman came and got the children from their beds. They received their little pieces of bread, even less than the last time. On the way to the woods, Hansel crumbled his piece in his pocket, then often stood still, and threw crumbs onto the ground.

"Hansel, why are you always stopping and looking around?" said his father. "Keep walking straight ahead."

"I can see my pigeon sitting on the roof. It wants to say good-bye to me."

"Fool," said the woman, "that isn't your pigeon. That's the morning sun shining on the chimney."

But little by little Hansel dropped all the crumbs onto the path. The woman took them deeper into the woods than they had ever been in their whole lifetime.

Once again a large fire was made, and the mother said, "Sit here, children. If you get tired you can sleep a little. We are going into the woods to cut wood. We will come and get you in the evening when we are finished."

When it was midday Gretel shared her bread with Hansel, who had scattered his piece along the path. Then they fell asleep, and evening passed, but no one came to get the poor children.

It was dark at night when they awoke, and Hansel comforted Greteland said, "Wait, when the moon comes up I will be able to see the crumbs of bread that I scattered, and they will show us the way back home."

When the moon appeared they got up, but they could not find any crumbs, for the many thousands of birds that fly about in the woods and in the fields had pecked them up.

Hansel said to Gretel, "We will find our way," but they did not find it.

They walked through the entire night and the next day from morning until evening, but they did not find their way out of the woods. They were terribly hungry, for they had eaten only a few small berries that were growing on the ground. And because they were so tired that their legs would no longer carry them, they lay down under a tree and fell asleep. It was already the third morning since they had left the father's house. They started walking again, but managed only to go deeper and deeper into the woods. If help did not come soon, they would perish. At midday they saw a little snow-white bird sitting on a branch. It sang so beautifully that they stopped to listen. When it was finished it stretched its wings and flew in front of them. They followed it until they came to a little house. The bird sat on the roof, and when they came closer, they saw that the little house was built entirely from bread with a roof made of cake, and the windows were made of clear sugar.

"Let's help ourselves to a good meal," said Hansel. "I'll eat a piece of the roof, and Gretel, you eat from the window. That will be sweet."

Hansel reached up and broke off a little of the roof to see how it tasted,while Gretel stood next to the windowpanes and was nibbling at them. Then a gentle voice called out from inside:

Nibble, nibble, little mouse, Who is nibbling at my house?

The children answered:

The wind, the wind, The heavenly child.

They continued to eat, without being distracted. Hansel, who very much like the taste of the roof, tore down another large piece, and Gretel poked out an entire round windowpane. Suddenly the door opened, and a woman, as old as the hills and leaning on a crutch, came creeping out. Hansel and Gretel were so frightened that they dropped what they were holding in their hands.

But the old woman shook her head and said,"Oh, you dear children, who brought you here? Just come in and stay with me. No harm will come to you."

She took them by the hand and led them into her house.Then she served them a good meal: milk and pancakes with sugar, apples, and nuts. Afterward she made two nice beds for them, decked in white. Hansel and Gretel went to bed, thinking they were in heaven. But the old woman had only pretended to be friendly. She was a wicked witch who was lying in wait there for children. She had built her house of bread only in order to lure them to her, and if she captured one, she would kill him, cook him, and eat him; and for her that was a day to celebrate.

Witches have red eyes and cannot see very far, but they have a sense of smell like animals, and know when humans are approaching.

When Hansel and Gretel came near to her, she laughed wickedly and spoke scornfully, "Now I have them. They will not get away from me again."

Early the next morning, before they awoke, she got up, went to their beds, and looked at the two of them lying there so peacefully, with their full red cheeks. "They will be a good mouthful," she mumbled to herself. Then she grabbed Hansel with her withered hand and carried him to a little stall, where she locked him behind a cage door. Cry as he might, there was no help for him.

Then she shook Gretel and cried, "Get up, lazybones! Fetch water and cook something good for your brother. He is locked outside in the stall and is to be fattened up. When he is fat I am going to eat him."

Gretel began to cry, but it was all for nothing. She had to do what the witch demanded. Now Hansel was given the best things to eat every day, but Gretel received nothing but crayfish shells.

>Every morning the old woman crept out to the stall and shouted, "Hansel, stick out your finger, so I can feel if you are fat yet."

But Hansel stuck out a little bone, and the old woman, who had bad eyes and could not see the bone, thought it was Hansel's finger, and she wondered why he didn't get fat.

When four weeks had passed and Hansel was still thin, impatience overcame her, and she would wait no longer. "Hey, Gretel!" she shouted to the girl, "Hurry up and fetch some water. Whether Hansel is fat or thin, tomorrow I am going to slaughter him and boil him."

Oh, how the poor little sister sobbed as she was forced to carry the water, and how the tears streamed down her cheeks! "Dear God, please help us,"she cried. "If only the wild animals had devoured us in the woods, then we would have died together."

"Save your slobbering," said the old woman. "It doesn't help you at all."

The next morning Gretel had to get up early, hang up the kettle with water, and make a fire.

"First we are going to bake," said the old woman. "I have already made a fire in the oven and kneaded the dough."

She pushed poor Gretel outside to the oven, from which fiery flames were leaping. "Climb in," said the witch, "and see if it is hot enough to put the bread in yet." And when Gretel was inside, she intended to close the oven, and bake her, and eat her as well.

But Gretel saw what she had in mind, so she said,"I don't know how to do that. How can I get inside?"

"Stupid goose," said the old woman."The opening is big enough. See, I myself could get in." And she crawled up stuck her head into the oven.

Then Gretel gave her a shove, causing her to fall in. Then she closed the iron door and secured it with a bar. The old woman began to howl frightfully. But Gretel ran away, and the godless witch burned up miserably. Gretel ran straight to Hansel, unlocked his stall, and cried, "Hansel, we are saved. The old witch is dead."

Then Hansel jumped out, like a bird from its cage when someone opens its door.How happy they were!They threw their arms around each other's necks, jumped with joy, and kissed one another. Because they now had nothing to fear, they went into the witch's house. In every corner were chests of pearls and precious stones.

"These are better than pebbles," said Hansel, filling his pockets.

Gretel said, "I will take some home with me as well," and she filled her apron full.

"But now we must leave," said Hansel, "and get out of these witch-woods."

After walking a few hours they arrived at a large body of water. "We cannot get across," said Hansel. "I cannot see a walkway or a bridge."

"There are no boats here," answered Gretel, "but there is a white duck swimming. If I ask it, it will help us across."

Then she called out:

Duckling, duckling, Here stand Gretel and Hansel. Neither a walkway nor a bridge, Take us onto your white back.

The duckling came up to them, and Hansel climbed onto it, then asked his little sister to sit down next to him.

"No," answered Gretel. "That would be too heavy for the duckling. It should take us across one at a time."

That is what the good animal did, and when they were safely on the other side, and had walked on a little while, the woods grew more and more familiar to them, and finally they saw the father's house in the distance. They began to run, rushed inside, and threw their arms around the father's neck.

The man had not had even one happy hour since he had left the children in the woods. However, the woman had died. Gretel shook out her apron, scattering pearls and precious stones around the room, and Hansel added to them by throwing one handful after the other from his pockets.

Now all their cares were at an end, and they lived happily together.

My tale is done,A mouse has run.

And whoever catches it can make for himself from it a large, large fur cap.

Vor einem großen Walde wohnte ein ar- mer Holzhacker, der hatte nichts zu beißen und zu brechen, und kaum das tägliche Brod für seine Frau und seine zwei Kinder, Hänsel und Gretel. Einmal konnte er auch das nicht mehr schaffen, und wußte sich nicht zu helfen in seiner Noth. Wie er Abends vor Sorge sich im Bett herumwälzte, da sagte seine Frau zu ihm: „höre Mann, morgen früh nimm die beiden Kinder, gieb jedem noch ein Stückchen Brod, dann führ sie hinaus in den Wald, mitten inne, wo er am dicksten ist, da mach ihnen ein Feuer an, und dann geh weg und laß sie dort, wir kön- nen sie nicht länger ernähren.“ „Nein Frau, sagte der Mann, das kann ich nicht über mein Herz bringen, meine eigenen lieben Kinder zu den wilden Thieren zu führen, die sie bald in dem Wald zerreißen würden.“ „Wenn du das nicht thust, sprach die Frau, so müssen wir alle miteinander Hungers sterben;“ da ließ sie ihm keine Ruhe, bis er Ja sagte.

Die zwei Kinder waren auch noch wach von Hunger, und hatten alles gehört, was die Mutter zum Vater gesagt hatte. Gretel dach- te, nun ist es um mich geschehen und fing er- bärmlich an zu weinen, Hänsel aber sprach: „sey still, Gretel, und gräm dich nicht, ich will uns helfen.“ Damit stieg er auf, zog sein Röcklein an, machte die Unterthüre auf und schlich hinaus. Da schien der Mond hell und die weißen Kieselsteine glänzten wie lauter Ba- tzen. Hänsel bückte sich und machte sich sein ganz Rocktäschlein voll davon, so viel nur hin- ein wollten, dann ging er zurück ins Haus: „tröste dich, Gretel, und schlaf nur ruhig,“ leg- te sich wieder ins Bett und schlief ein.

Morgens früh, ehe die Sonne noch aufge- gangen war, kam die Mutter und weckte sie alle beide: „steht auf, ihr Kinder, wir wollen in den Wald gehen, da habt ihr jedes ein Stück- lein Brod, aber haltets zu Rathe und hebts euch für den Mittag auf.“ Gretel nahm das Brod unter die Schürze, weil Hänsel die Stei- ne in der Tasche hatte, dann machten sie sich auf den Weg in den Wald hinein. Wie sie ein Weilchen gegangen waren, stand Hänsel still und guckte nach dem Haus zurück, bald darauf wieder und immer wieder. Der Vater sprach: „Hänsel, was guckst du zurück und hältst dich auf, hab Acht und marschir zu.“ „Ach, Vater, ich seh nach meinem weißen Kätz- chen, das sitzt oben auf dem Dach und will mir Ade sagen.“ Die Mutter sprach: „ei Narr, das ist dein Kätzchen nicht, das ist die Morgensonne, die auf den Schornstein scheint.“ Hänsel aber hatte nicht nach dem Kätzchen gese- hen, sondern immer einen von den blanken Kiesel- steinen aus seiner Tasche auf den Weg geworfen.

Wie sie mitten in den Wald gekommen waren, sprach der Vater, „nun sammelt Holz, ihr Kinder, ich will ein Feuer anmachen, daß wir nicht frieren.“ Hänsel und Gretel trugen Reisig zusammen, einen kleinen Berg hoch. Da steckten sie es an, und wie die Flamme recht groß brannte, sagte die Mutter „nun legt euch ans Feuer und schlaft, wir wollen in dem Wald das Holz fällen, wartet, bis wir wieder kommen, und euch abholen.“

Hänsel und Gretel saßen an dem Feuer, bis Mittag, da aß jedes sein Stücklein Brod, und dann wieder bis an den Abend; aber Va- ter und Mutter blieben aus, und niemand woll- te kommen und sie abholen. Wie es nun fin- stere Nacht wurde, fing Gretel an zu weinen, Hänsel aber sprach: „wart nur ein Weilchen, bis der Mond aufgegangen ist.“ Und als der Mond aufgegangen war, faßte er die Gre- tel bei der Hand, da lagen die Kieselsteine wie neugeschlagene Batzen und schimmerten und zeigten ihnen den Weg. Da gingen sie die ganze Nacht durch, und wie es Morgen war, kamen sie wieder bei ihres Vaters Haus an. Der Vater freute sich von Herzen, als er seine Kinder wieder sah, denn er hatte sie ungern allein gelassen, die Mutter stellte sich auch, als wenn sie sich freute, heimlich aber war sie bös.

Nicht lange darnach, war wieder kein Brod im Hause und Hänsel und Gretel hörten wie Abends die Mutter zum Vater sagte: „einmal haben die Kinder den Weg zurückgefunden, und da habe ichs gut seyn lassen, aber jetzt ist wie- der nichts, als nur noch ein halber Laib Brod im Haus, du mußt sie morgen tiefer in den Wald führen, daß sie nicht wieder heim kom- men können, es ist sonst keine Hülfe für uns mehr.“ Dem Mann fiels schwer aufs Herz, und er gedachte, es wäre doch besser, wenn du den letzten Bissen mit deinen Kindern theiltest, weil er es aber einmal gethan hatte, so durfte er nicht nein sagen. Hänsel und Gretel hörten das Gespräch der Eltern; Hänsel stand auf und wollte wieder Kieselsteine auflesen, wie er aber an die Thüre kam, da hatte sie die Mutter zu- geschlossen. Doch tröstete er die Gretel und sprach: „schlaf nur, lieb Gretel, der liebe Gott wird uns schon helfen.“

Morgens früh erhielten sie ihr Stücklein Brod, noch kleiner als das vorigemal. Auf dem Wege bröckelte es Hänsel in der Tasche, stand oft still, und warf ein Bröcklein an die Erde. „Was bleibst du immer stehen, Hänsel, und guckst dich um, sagte der Vater, geh dei- ner Wege.“ „Ach! ich seh nach meinem Täubchen, das sitzt auf dem Dach und will mir Ade sagen“ „du Narr, sagte die Mutter, das ist dein Täubchen nicht, das ist die Morgenson- ne, die auf den Schornstein oben scheint.“ Hänsel aber zerbröckelte all sein Brod und warf die Bröcklein auf den Weg.

Die Mutter aber führte sie noch tiefer in den Wald hinein, wo sie ihr Lebtag nicht ge- wesen waren, da sollten sie wieder einschlafen bei einem großen Feuer, und Abends wollten die Eltern kommen und sie abholen. Zu Mit- tag theilte Gretel ihr Brod mit Hänsel, weil der seins all auf den Weg gestreut; der Mit- tag verging und der Abend verging, aber nie- mand kam zu den armen Kindern. Hänsel trö- stete die Gretel und sagte: „wart, wenn der Mond aufgeht, dann seh ich die Bröcklein Brod, die ich ausgestreut habe, die zeigen uns den Weg nach Haus.“ Der Mond ging auf, wie aber Hänsel nach den Bröcklein sah, da waren sie weg, die viel tausend Vöglein in dem Wald, die hatten sie gefunden und aufgepickt. Hänsel meinte doch den Weg nach Haus zu finden und zog die Gretel mit sich, aber sie ver- irrten sich bald in der großen Wildniß und gingen die Nacht und den ganzen Tag, da schliefen sie vor Müdigkeit ein; und gingen noch einen Tag, aber sie kamen nicht aus den Wald heraus, und waren so hungrig, denn sie hatten nichts zu essen, als ein paar kleine Beer- lein, die auf der Erde standen.

Am dritten Tage gingen sie wieder bis zu Mittag, da kamen sie an ein Häuslein, das war ganz aus Brod gebaut und war mit Ku- chen gedeckt, und die Fenster waren von hellem Zucker. „Da wollen wir uns niedersetzen und uns satt essen, sagte Hänsel; ich will vom Dach essen, iß du vom Fenster, Gretel, das ist fein süß für dich.“ Hänsel hatte schon ein gut Stück vom Dach und Gretel schon ein paar runde Fensterscheiben gegessen, und brach sich eben eine neue aus, da hörten sie eine feine Stimme, die von innen herausrief: „knuper, knuper, Kneischen! „wer knupert an meinem Häuschen!“ Hänsel und Gretel erschracken so gewaltig, daß sie fallen ließen, was sie in der Hand hielten, und gleich darauf sahen sie aus der Thüre eine kleine steinalte Frau schleichen. Sie wackelte mit dem Kopf und sagte: „ei, ihr lieben Kin- der, wo seyd ihr denn hergelaufen, kommt her- ein mit mir, ihr sollts gut haben,“ faßte beide an der Hand und führte sie in ihr Häuschen. Da ward gutes Essen aufgetragen, Milch und Pfannkuchen mit Zucker, Aepfel und Nüsse, und dann wurden zwei schöne Bettlein bereitet, da legten sich Hänsel und Gretel hinein, und meinten sie wären wie im Himmel.

Die Alte aber war eine böse Hexe, die lauerte den Kindern auf, und hatte um sie zu locken ihr Brodhäuslein gebaut, und wenn eins in ihre Gewalt kam, da machte sie es todt, kochte es und aß es, und das war ihr ein Fest- tag. Da war sie nun recht froh, wie Hänsel und Gretel ihr zugelaufen kamen. Früh, ehe sie noch erwacht waren, stand sie schon auf, ging an ihre Bettlein und wie sie die zwei so lieblich ruhen sah, freute sie sich und gedachte, das wird ein guter Bissen für dich seyn. Sie packte Hänsel und steckte ihn in einen kleinen Stall, und wie er da aufwachte, war er von einem Gitter umschlossen, wie man junge Hühn- lein einsperrt, und konnte nur ein paar Schritte gehen. Das Gretel aber schüttelte sie und rief: steh auf, du Faullenzerin, hol Wasser und geh in die Küche und koch gut zu essen, dort steckt dein Bruder in einem Stall, den will ich erst fett machen, und wann er fett ist, dann will ich ihn essen, jetzt sollst du ihn füttern. Gre- tel erschrack und weinte, mußte aber thun, was die Hexe verlangte. Da ward nun alle Tage dem Hänsel das beste Essen gekocht, daß er fett werden sollte, Gretel aber bekam nichts, als die Krebsschalen, und alle Tage kam die Alte und sagte: „Hänsel, streck deine Finger heraus, daß ich fühle, ob du bald fett genug bist.“ Hänsel streckte ihr aber immer ein Knöch- lein heraus, da verwunderte sie sich, daß er gar nicht zunehmen wolle.

Nach vier Wochen sagte sie eines Abends zu Gretel: „sey flink, geh und trag Wasser herbei, dein Brüderchen mag nun fett genug seyn oder nicht, morgen will ich es schlachten und sieden, ich will derweile den Teig anma- chen, daß wir auch dazu backen können. Da ging Gretel mit traurigem Herzen und trug das Wasser, worin Hänsel sollte gesotten wer- den. Früh Morgens mußte Gretel aufstehen, Feuer anmachen und den Kessel mit Wasser aufhängen. „Gieb nun Acht, bis es siedet, sag- te die Hexe, ich will Feuer in den Backofen machen und das Brod hineinschieben;“ Gretel stand in der Küche und weinte blutige Thrä- nen, und dachte, hätten uns lieber die wilden Thiere im Walde gefressen, so wären wir zu- sammen gestorben und müßten nun nicht das Herzeleid tragen, und ich müßte nicht selber das Wasser zu dem Tod meines lieben Bruders sieden, du lieber Gott, hilf uns armen Kin- dern aus der Noth.

Da rief die Alte: „Gretel komm gleich einmal hierher zu dem Backofen,“ wie Gretel kam, sagte sie: „guck hinein, ob das Brod schon hübsch braun und gar ist, meine Augen sind schwach, ich kann nicht so weit sehen, und wenn du auch nicht kannst, so setz dich auf das Brett, so will ich dich hineinschieben, da kannst du darin herumgehen und nachsehen.“ Wenn aber Gretel darin war, da wollte sie zumachen und Gretel sollte in dem heißen Ofen backen, und sie wollte es auch aufessen: das dachte die böse Hexe, und darum hatte sie das Gretel ge- rufen. Gott gab es aber Gretel ein und sie sagte: „ich weiß nicht, wie ich das anfangen soll, zeigs mirs erst, setz dich drauf, ich will dich hin- einschieben.“ Und die Alte setzte sich auf das Brett, und weil sie leicht war, schob sie Gretel hinein so weit sie konnte, und dann machte sie geschwind die Thüre zu, und steckte den eisernen Riegel vor. Da fing die Alte an in dem heißen Back- ofen zu schreien und zu jammern, Gretel aber lief fort, und sie mußte elendiglich verbrennen.

Und Gretel lief zum Hänsel, machte ihm sein Thürchen auf und Hänsel sprang heraus, und sie küßten sich einander und waren froh. Das ganze Häuschen war voll von Edelgestei- nen und Perlen, davon füllten sie ihre Taschen, gingen fort und fanden den Weg nach Haus. Der Vater freute sich als er sie wieder sah, er hatte keinen vergnügten Tag gehabt, seit seine Kinder fort waren, und ward nun ein reicher Mann. Die Mutter aber war gestorben.

The Juniper Tree

German Version

English Version

While beginning to mark-up The Juniper Tree from the original source for the German text, the team discovered that it was in Low German instead of Standard German. Efforts to find a usable German version that we felt confident in from other sources proved unsuccessful. We have decided to include only the English version of The Juniper Tree as it still offers interesting data as to our main research question of the Grimms' portrayal of women characters.

Long ago, at least two thousand years, there was a rich man who had a beautiful and pious wife, and they loved each other dearly. However, they had no children, though they wished very much to have some, and the woman prayed for them day and night, but they didn't get any, and they didn't get any.

In front of their house there was a courtyard where there stood a juniper tree. One day in winter the woman was standing beneath it, peeling herself an apple, and while she was thus peeling the apple, she cut her finger, and the blood fell into the snow.

"Oh," said the woman. She sighed heavily, looked at the blood before her, and was most unhappy. "If only I had a child as red as blood and as white as snow." And as she said that, she became quite contented, and felt sure that it was going to happen.

Then she went into the house, and a month went by, and the snow was gone. And two months, and everything was green. And three months, and all the flowers came out of the earth. And four months, and all the trees in the woods grew thicker, and the green branches were all entwined in one another, and the birds sang until the woods resounded and the blossoms fell from the trees. Then the fifth month passed, and she stood beneath the juniper tree, which smelled so sweet that her heart jumped for joy, and she fell on her knees and was beside herself. And when the sixth month was over, the fruit was thick and large, and then she was quite still. And after the seventh month she picked the juniper berries and ate them greedily. Then she grew sick and sorrowful. Then the eighth month passed, and she called her husband to her, and cried, and said, "If I die, then bury me beneath the juniper tree." Then she was quite comforted and happy until the next month was over, and then she had a child as white as snow and as red as blood, and when she saw it, she was so happy that she died.

Her husband buried her beneath the juniper tree, and he began to cry bitterly. After some time he was more at ease, and although he still cried, he could bear it. And some time later he took another wife.

He had a daughter by the second wife, but the first wife's child was a little son, and he was as red as blood and as white as snow. When the woman looked at her daughter, she loved her very much, but then she looked at the little boy, and it pierced her heart, for she thought that he would always stand in her way, and she was always thinking how she could get the entire inheritance for her daughter. And the Evil One filled her mind with this until she grew very angry with the little boy, and she pushed him from one corner to the other and slapped him here and cuffed him there, until the poor child was always afraid, for when he came home from school there was nowhere he could find any peace.

One day the woman had gone upstairs to her room, when her little daughter came up too, and said, "Mother, give me an apple." "Yes, my child," said the woman,and gave her a beautiful apple out of the chest. The chest had a large heavy lid with a large sharp iron lock. "Mother," said the little daughter, "is brother not to have one too?" This made the woman angry, but she said, "Yes, when he comes home from school."

When from the window she saw him coming, it was as though the Evil One came over her, and she grabbed the apple and took it away from her daughter, saying, "You shall not have one before your brother." She threw the apple into the chest, and shut it. Then the little boy came in the door, and the Evil One made her say to him kindly, "My son, do you want an apple?" And she looked at him fiercely. "Mother," said the little boy, "how angry you look. Yes, give me an apple." Then it seemed to her as if she had to persuade him. "Come with me," she said, opening the lid of the chest. "Take out an apple for yourself." And while the little boy was leaning over, the Evil One prompted her, and crash! she slammed down the lid, and his head flew off, falling among the red apples.

Then fear overcame her, and she thought, "Maybe I can get out of this." So she went upstairs to her room to her chest of drawers, and took a white scarf out of the top drawer, and set the head on the neck again, tying the scarf around it so that nothing could be seen. Then she set him on a chair in front of the door and put the apple in his hand. After this Marlene came into the kitchen to her mother, who was standing by the fire with a pot of hot water before her which she was stirring around and around. "Mother," said Marlene, "brother is sitting at the door, and he looks totally white and has an apple in his hand. I asked him to give me the apple, but he did not answer me, and I was very frightened." "Go back to him," said her mother, "and if he will not answer you, then box his ears." So Marlene went to him and said, "Brother, give me the apple." But he was silent, so she gave him one on the ear, and his head fell off. Marlene was terrified, and began crying and screaming, and ran to her mother, and said, "Oh, mother, I have knocked my brother's head off," and she cried and cried and could not be comforted. "Marlene," said the mother, "what have you done? Be quiet and don't let anyone know about it. It cannot be helped now. We will cook him into stew." Then the mother took the little boy and chopped him in pieces, put him into the pot, and cooked him into stew. But Marlene stood by crying and crying, and all her tears fell into the pot, and they did not need any salt.

Then the father came home, and sat down at the table and said, "Where is my son?" And the mother served up a large, large dish of stew, and Marlene cried and could not stop. Then the father said again, "Where is my son?" "Oh," said the mother, "he has gone across the country to his mother's great uncle. He will stay there awhile." "What is he doing there? He did not even say good-bye to me." "Oh, he wanted to go, and asked me if he could stay six weeks. He will be well taken care of there." "Oh," said the man, "I am unhappy. It isn't right. He should have said good-bye to me." With that he began to eat, saying, "Marlene, why are you crying? Your brother will certainly come back." Then he said, "Wife, this food is delicious. Give me some more." And the more he ate the more he wanted, and he said, "Give me some more. You two shall have none of it. It seems to me as if it were all mine." And he ate and ate, throwing all the bones under the table, until he had finished it all.

Marlene went to her chest of drawers, took her best silk scarf from the bottom drawer, and gathered all the bones from beneath the table and tied them up in her silk scarf, then carried them outside the door, crying tears of blood. She laid them down beneath the juniper tree on the green grass, and after she had put them there, she suddenly felt better and did not cry anymore.

Then the juniper tree began to move. The branches moved apart, then moved together again, just as if someone were rejoicing and clapping his hands. At the same time a mist seemed to rise from the tree, and in the center of this mist it burned like a fire, and a beautiful bird flew out of the fire singing magnificently, and it flew high into the air, and when it was gone, the juniper tree was just as it had been before, and the cloth with the bones was no longer there. Marlene, however, was as happy and contented as if her brother were still alive. And she went merrily into the house, sat down at the table, and ate.

Then the bird flew away and lit on a goldsmith's house, and began to sing: My mother, she killed me, My father, he ate me, My sister Marlene, Gathered all my bones, Tied them in a silken scarf, Laid them beneath the juniper tree, Tweet, tweet, what a beautiful bird am I.

The goldsmith was sitting in his workshop making a golden chain, when he heard the bird sitting on his roof and singing. The song seemed very beautiful to him. He stood up, but as he crossed the threshold he lost one of his slippers. However, he went right up the middle of the street with only one slipper and one sock on. He had his leather apron on, and in one hand he had a golden chain and in the other his tongs. The sun was shining brightly on the street. He walked onward, then stood still and said to the bird, "Bird," he said, "how beautifully you can sing. Sing that piece again for me." "No," said the bird, "I do not sing twice for nothing. Give me the golden chain, and then I will sing it again for you." The goldsmith said, "Here is the golden chain for you. Now sing that song again for me." Then the bird came and took the golden chain in his right claw, and went and sat in front of the goldsmith, and sang: My mother, she killed me, My father, he ate me, My sister Marlene, Gathered all my bones, Tied them in a silken scarf, Laid them beneath the juniper tree, Tweet, tweet, what a beautiful bird am I.

Then the bird flew away to a shoemaker, and lit on his roof and sang: My mother, she killed me, My father, he ate me, My sister Marlene, Gathered all my bones, Tied them in a silken scarf, Laid them beneath the juniper tree, Tweet, tweet, what a beautiful bird am I. Hearing this, the shoemaker ran out of doors in his shirtsleeves, and looked up at his roof, and had to hold his hand in front of his eyes to keep the sun from blinding him. "Bird," said he, "how beautifully you can sing." Then he called in at his door, "Wife, come outside. There is a bird here. Look at this bird. He certainly can sing." Then he called his daughter and her children, and the journeyman, and the apprentice, and the maid, and they all came out into the street and looked at the bird and saw how beautiful he was, and what fine red and green feathers he had, and how his neck was like pure gold, and how his eyes shone like stars in his head. "Bird," said the shoemaker, "now sing that song again for me." "No," said the bird, "I do not sing twice for nothing. You must give me something." "Wife," said the man, "go into the shop. There is a pair of red shoes on the top shelf. Bring them down." Then the wife went and brought the shoes. "There, bird," said the man, "now sing that piece again for me." Then the bird came and took the shoes in his left claw, and flew back to the roof, and sang: My mother, she killed me, My father, he ate me, My sister Marlene, Gathered all my bones, Tied them in a silken scarf, Laid them beneath the juniper tree, Tweet, tweet, what a beautiful bird am I.

When he had finished his song he flew away. In his right claw he had the chain and in his left one the shoes. He flew far away to a mill, and the mill went clickety-clack, clickety-clack, clickety-clack. In the mill sat twenty miller's apprentices cutting a stone, and chiseling chip-chop, chip-chop, chip-chop. And the mill went clickety-clack, clickety-clack, clickety-clack. Then the bird went and sat on a linden tree which stood in front of the mill, and sang: My mother, she killed me, Then one of them stopped working. My father, he ate me, Then two more stopped working and listened, My sister Marlene, Then four more stopped, Gathered all my bones, Tied them in a silken scarf, Now only eight only were chiseling, Laid them beneath Now only five, the juniper tree, Now only one, Tweet, tweet, what a beautiful bird am I.

Then the last one stopped also, and heard the last words. "Bird," said he, "how beautifully you sing. Let me hear that too. Sing it once more for me." "No," said the bird, "I do not sing twice for nothing. Give me the millstone, and then I will sing it again." "Yes," he said, "if it belonged only to me, you should have it." "Yes," said the others, "if he sings again he can have it." Then the bird came down, and the twenty millers took a beam and lifted the stone up. Yo-heave-ho! Yo-heave-ho! Yo-heave-ho! The bird stuck his neck through the hole and put the stone on as if it were a collar, then flew to the tree again, and sang: My mother, she killed me, My father, he ate me, My sister Marlene, Gathered all my bones, Tied them in a silken scarf, Laid them beneath the juniper tree, Tweet, tweet, what a beautiful bird am I.

When he was finished singing, he spread his wings, and in his right claw he had the chain, and in his left one the shoes, and around his neck the millstone. He flew far away to his father's house. In the room the father, the mother, and Marlene were sitting at the table. The father said, "I feel so contented. I am so happy." "Not I," said the mother, "I feel uneasy, just as if a bad storm were coming." But Marlene just sat and cried and cried. Then the bird flew up, and as it seated itself on the roof, the father said, "Oh, I feel so truly happy, and the sun is shining so beautifully outside. I feel as if I were about to see some old acquaintance again." "Not I," said the woman,"I am so afraid that my teeth are chattering, and I feel like I have fire in my veins." And she tore open her bodice even more. Marlene sat in a corner crying. She held a handkerchief before her eyes and cried until it was wet clear through.

Then the bird seated itself on the juniper tree, and sang: My mother, she killed me, The mother stopped her ears and shut her eyes, not wanting to see or hear, but there was a roaring in her ears like the fiercest storm, and her eyes burned and flashed like lightning. My father, he ate me, "Oh, mother," said the man, "that is a beautiful bird. He is singing so splendidly, and the sun is shining so warmly, and it smells like pure cinnamon." My sister Marlene, Then Marlene laid her head on her knees and cried and cried, but the man said, "I am going out. I must see the bird up close." "Oh, don't go," said the woman, "I feel as if the whole house were shaking and on fire." But the man went out and looked at the bird. Gathered all my bones, Tied them in a silken scarf, Laid them beneath the juniper tree, Tweet, tweet, what a beautiful bird am I.

With this the bird dropped the golden chain, and it fell right around the man's neck, so exactly around it that it fit beautifully. Then the man went in and said, "Just look what a beautiful bird that is, and what a beautiful golden chain he has given me, and how nice it looks." But the woman was terrified. She fell down on the floor in the room, and her cap fell off her head. Then the bird sang once more: My mother killed me. "I wish I were a thousand fathoms beneath the earth, so I would not have to hear that!" My father, he ate me, Then the woman fell down as if she were dead. My sister Marlene, "Oh," said Marlene, "I too will go out and see if the bird will give me something." Then she went out. Gathered all my bones, Tied them in a silken scarf, He threw the shoes down to her. Laid them beneath the juniper tree, Tweet, tweet, what a beautiful bird am I. Then she was contented and happy. She put on the new red shoes and danced and leaped into the house. "Oh," she said, "I was so sad when I went out and now I am so contented. That is a splendid bird, he has given me a pair of red shoes." "No," said the woman, jumping to her feet and with her hair standing up like flames of fire, "I feel as if the world were coming to an end. I too, will go out and see if it makes me feel better." And as she went out the door, crash! the bird threw the millstone on her head, and it crushed her to death. The father and Marlene heard it and went out. Smoke, flames, and fire were rising from the place, and when that was over, the little brother was standing there, and he took his father and Marlene by the hand, and all three were very happy, and they went into the house, sat down at the table, and ate.

Rapunzel

English Version

German Version

Once upon a time there was a man and a woman who had long, but to no avail, wished for a child. Finally the woman came to believe that the good Lord would fulfill her wish. Through the small rear window of these people's house they could see into a splendid garden that was filled with the most beautiful flowers and herbs. The garden was surrounded by a high wall, and no one dared enter, because it belonged to a sorceress who possessed great power and was feared by everyone.

One day the woman was standing at this window, and she saw a bed planted with the most beautiful rapunzel. It looked so fresh and green that she longed for some. It was her greatest desire to eat some of the rapunzel. This desire increased with every day, and not knowing how to get any, she became miserably ill.

Her husband was frightened, and asked her, "What ails you, dear wife?"

"Oh,"she answered,"if I do not get some rapunzel from the garden behind our house, I shall die."

The man, who loved her dearly, thought, "Before you let your wife die, you must get her some of the rapunzel, whatever the cost."

So just as it was getting dark he climbed over the high wall into the sorceress's garden, hastily dug up a handful of rapunzel, and took it to his wife. She immediately made a salad from it, which she devoured eagerly. It tasted so very good to her that by the next day her desire for more had grown threefold. If she were to have any peace, the man would have to climb into the garden once again. Thus he set forth once again just as it was getting dark. But no sooner than he had climbed over the wall than, to his horror, he saw the sorceress standing there before him.

"How can you dare," she asked with an angry look, "to climb into my garden and like a thief to steal my rapunzel? You will pay for this."

"Oh," he answered, "Let mercy overrule justice. I came to do this out of necessity. My wife saw your rapunzel from our window, and such a longing came over her, that she would die, if she did not get some to eat."

The sorceress's anger abated somewhat, and she said, If things are as you say, I will allow you to take as much rapunzel as you want. But under one condition: You must give me the child that your wife will bring to the world. It will do well, and I will take care of it like a mother."

In his fear the man agreed to everything.

When the woman gave birth, the sorceress appeared, named the little girl Rapunzel, and took her away. Rapunzel became the most beautiful child under the sun. When she was twelve years old, the sorceress locked her in a tower that stood in a forest and that had neither a door nor a stairway, but only a tiny little window at the very top.

When the sorceress wanted to enter, she stood below and called out:

Rapunzel, Rapunzel, Let down your hair to me.

Rapunzel had splendid long hair, as fine as spun gold. When she heard the sorceress's voice, she untied her braids, wound them around a window hook, let her hair fall twenty yards to the ground, and the sorceress climbed up it.

A few years later it happened that a king's son was riding through the forest. As he approached the tower he heard a song so beautiful that he stopped to listen. It was Rapunzel, who was passing the time by singing with her sweet voice. The prince wanted to climb up to her, and looked for a door in the tower, but none was to be found.

He rode home, but the song had so touched his heart that he returned to the forest every day and listened to it. One time, as he was thus standing behind a tree, he saw the sorceress approach, and heard her say:

Rapunzel, Rapunzel, Let down your hair.

Then Rapunzel let down her strands of hair, and the sorceress climbed up them to her.

"If that is the ladder into the tower, then sometime I will try my luck."

And the next day, just as it was beginning to get dark, he went to the tower and called out:

Rapunzel, Rapunzel, Let down your hair.

The hair fell down, and the prince climbed up.

At first Rapunzel was terribly frightened when a man such as she had never seen before came in to her. However, the prince began talking to her in a very friendly manner, telling her that his heart had been so touched by her singing that he could have no peace until he had seen her in person. Then Rapunzel lost her fear, and when he asked her if she would take him as her husband, she thought, He would rather have me than would old Frau Gothel." She said yes and placed her hand into his.

She said, I would go with you gladly, but I do not know how to get down. Every time that you come, bring a strand of silk, from which I will weave a ladder. When it is finished I will climb down, and you can take me away on your horse." They arranged that he would come to her every evening, for the old woman came by day.

The sorceress did not notice what was happening until one day Rapunzel said to her, Frau Gothel, tell me why it is that you are more difficult to pull up than is the young prince, who will be arriving any moment now?"

"You godless child," cried the sorceress. "What am I hearing from you? I thought I had removed you from the whole world, but you have deceived me nonetheless."

In her anger she grabbed Rapunzel's beautiful hair, wrapped it a few times around her left hand, grasped a pair of scissors with her right hand, and snip snap, cut it off. And she was so unmerciful that she took Rapunzel into a wilderness where she suffered greatly.

On the evening of the same day that she sent Rapunzel away, the sorceress tied the cut-off hair to the hook at the top of the tower, and when the prince called out:

Rapunzel, Rapunzel, Let down your hair.

she let down the hair.

The prince climbed up, but above, instead of his beloved Rapunzel, he found the sorceress, who peered at him with poisonous and evil looks.

"Aha!" she cried scornfully. "You have come for your Mistress Darling, but that beautiful bird is no longer sitting in her nest, nor is she singing any more. The cat got her, and will scratch your eyes out as well. You have lost Rapunzel. You will never see her again."

The prince was overcome with grief, and in his despair he threw himself from the tower. He escaped with his life, but the thorns into which he fell poked out his eyes. Blind, he wandered about in the forest, eating nothing but grass and roots, and doing nothing but weeping and wailing over the loss of his beloved wife. Thus he wandered about miserably for some years, finally happening into the wilderness where Rapunzel lived miserably with the twins that she had given birth to.

He heard a voice and thought it was familiar. He advanced toward it, and as he approached, Rapunzel recognized him, and crying, threw her arms around his neck. Two of her tears fell into his eyes, and they became clear once again, and he could see as well as before. He led her into his kingdom, where he was received with joy, and for a long time they lived happily and satisfied.

Es war einmal ein Mann und eine Frau, die hatten sich schon lange ein Kind gewünscht und nie eins bekommen, endlich aber ward die Frau guter Hoffnung. Diese Leute hatten in ihrem Hinterhaus ein kleines Fenster, daraus konnten sie in den Garten einer Fee sehen, der voll von Blumen und Kräutern stand, allerlei Art, keiner aber durfte es wagen, in den Gar- ten hineinzugehen. Eines Tages stand die Frau an diesem Fenster und sah hinab, da erblickte sie wunderschöne Rapunzeln auf einem Beet und wurde so lüstern darnach, und wußte doch, daß sie keine davon bekommen konnte, daß sie ganz abfiel und elend wurde. Ihr Mann erschrack endlich und fragte nach der Ursache; „ach wenn ich keine von den Rapunzeln aus dem Garten hinter unserm Haus zu essen kriege, so muß ich sterben.“ Der Mann, welcher sie gar lieb hatte, dachte, es mag kosten was es will, so willst du ihr doch welche schaffen, stieg eines Abends über die hohe Mauer und stach in aller Eile eine Hand voll Rapunzeln aus, die er seiner Frau brachte. Die Frau machte sich sogleich Salat daraus, und aß sie in vollem Heißhunger auf. Sie hat- ten ihr aber so gut, so gut geschmeckt, daß sie den andern Tag noch dreimal soviel Lust bekam. Der Mann sah wohl, daß keine Ruh wäre, also stieg er noch einmal in den Garten, allein er erschrack gewaltig, als die Fee darin stand und ihn heftig schalt, daß er es wage in ihren Gar- ten zu kommen und daraus zu stehlen. Er ent- schuldigte sich, so gut er konnte, mit der Schwan- gerschaft seiner Frau, und wie gefährlich es sey, ihr dann etwas abzuschlagen, endlich sprach die Fee: „ich will mich zufrieden geben und dir selbst gestatten Rapunzeln mitzunehmen, so viel du willst, wofern du mir das Kind geben wirst, womit deine Frau jetzo geht.“ In der Angst sagte der Mann alles zu, und als die Frau in Wochen kam, erschien die Fee sogleich, nannte das kleine Mädchen Rapunzel und nahm es mit sich fort.

Dieses Rapunzel wurde das schönste Kind unter der Sonne, wie es aber zwölf Jahr alt war, so schloß es die Fee in einen hohen hohen Thurm, der hatte weder Thür noch Treppe, nur bloß ganz oben war ein kleines Fensterchen. Wenn nun die Fee hinein wollte, so stand sie unten und rief:

„Rapunzel, Rapunzel! laß mir dein Haar herunter.“

Rapunzel hatte aber prächtige Haare, fein wie gesponnen Gold, und wenn die Fee so rief, so band sie sie los, wickelte sie oben um einen Fen- sterhaken und dann fielen die Haare zwanzig Ellen tief hinunter und die Fee stieg daran hinauf.

Eines Tages kam nun ein junger Königs- sohn durch den Wald, wo der Thurm stand, sah das schöne Rapunzel oben am Fenster ste- hen und hörte sie mit so süßer Stimme singen, daß er sich ganz in sie verliebte. Da aber keine Thüre im Thurm war und keine Leiter so hoch reichen konnte, so gerieth er in Verzweiflung, doch ging er alle Tage in den Wald hin, bis er einstmals die Fee kommen sah, die sprach:

„Rapunzel, Rapunzel! laß dein Haar herunter.“

Darauf sah er wohl, auf welcher Leiter man in den Thurm kommen konnte. Er hatte sich aber die Worte wohl gemerkt, die man sprechen muß- te, und des andern Tages, als es dunkel war, ging er an den Thurm und sprach hinauf:

„Rapunzel, Rapunzel, laß dein Haar herunter!“

da ließ sie die Haare los, und wie sie unten waren, machte er sich daran fest und wurde hin- aufgezogen.

Rapunzel erschrack nun anfangs, bald aber gefiel ihr der junge König so gut, daß sie mit ihm verabredete, er solle alle Tage kommen und hinaufgezogen werden. So lebten sie lustig und in Freuden eine geraume Zeit, und die Fee kam nicht dahinter, bis eines Tages das Rapunzel anfing und zu ihr sagte: „sag' sie mir doch Frau Gothel, meine Kleiderchen werden mir so eng und wollen nicht mehr passen.“ Ach du gottlo- ses Kind, sprach die Fee, was muß ich von dir hören, und sie merkte gleich, wie sie betrogen wäre, und war ganz aufgebracht. Da nahm sie die schönen Haare Rapunzels, schlug sie ein paar Mal um ihre linke Hand, griff eine Scheere mit der rechten und ritsch, ritsch, waren sie abge- schnitten. Darauf verwieß sie Rapunzel in eine Wüstenei, wo es ihr sehr kümmerlich erging und sie nach Verlauf einiger Zeit Zwillinge, einen Knaben und ein Mädchen gebar.

Denselben Tag aber, wo sie Rapunzel ver- stoßen hatte, machte die Fee Abends die abge- schnittenen Haare oben am Haken fest, und als der Königssohn kam;

„Rapunzel, Rapunzel, laß dein Haar herunter!“

so ließ sie zwar die Haare nieder, allein wie erstaunte der Prinz, als er statt seines gelieb- ten Rapunzels die Fee oben fand. „Weißt du was, sprach die erzürnte Fee, Rapunzel ist für dich Bösewicht auf immer verloren!“

Da wurde der Königssohn ganz verzwei- felnd, und stürzte sich gleich den Thurm hinab, das Leben brachte er davon, aber die beiden Augen hatte er sich ausgefallen, traurig irrte er im Wald herum, aß nichts als Gras und Wurzeln, und that nichts als weinen. Einige Jahre nachher geräth er in jene Wüstenei, wo Rapunzel kümmerlich mit ihren Kindern lebte, ihre Stimme däuchte ihm so bekannt, in dem- selben Augenblick erkannte sie ihn auch und fällt ihm um den Hals. Zwei von ihren Thrä- nen fallen in seine Augen, da werden sie wie- der klar, und er kann damit sehen, wie sonst.

Little Red Cap

English Version

German Version

Once upon a time there was a sweet little girl. Everyone who saw her liked her, but most of all her grandmother, who did not know what to give the child next. Once she gave her a little cap made of red velvet. Because it suited her so well, and she wanted to wear it all the time, she came to be known as Little Red Cap.

One day her mother said to her, "Come Little Red Cap. Here is a piece of cake and a bottle of wine. Take them to your grandmother. She is sick and weak, and they will do her well. Mind your manners and give her my greetings. Behave yourself on the way, and do not leave the path, or you might fall down and break the glass, and then there will be nothing for your grandmother. And when you enter her parlor, don't forget to say 'Good morning,' and don't peer into all the corners first."

"I'll do everything just right," said Little Red Cap, shaking her mother's hand.

The grandmother lived out in the woods, a half hour from the village. When Little Red Cap entered the woods a wolf came up to her. She did not know what a wicked animal he was, and was not afraid of him.

"Good day to you, Little Red Cap."

"Thank you, wolf."

"Where are you going so early, Little Red Cap?"

"To grandmother's."

"And what are you carrying under your apron?"

"Grandmother is sick and weak, and I am taking her some cake and wine. We baked yesterday, and they should be good for her and give her strength."

"Little Red Cap, just where does your grandmother live?"

"Her house is good quarter hour from here in the woods, under the three large oak trees. There's a hedge of hazel bushes there. You must know the place," said Little Red Cap.

The wolf thought to himself, "Now that sweet young thing is a tasty bite for me. She will taste even better than the old woman. You must be sly, and you can catch them both."

He walked along a little while with Little Red Cap, then he said, "Little Red Cap, just look at the beautiful flowers that are all around us. Why don't you go and take a look? And I don't believe you can hear how beautifully the birds are singing. You are walking along as though you were on your way to school. It is very beautiful in the woods."

Little Red Cap opened her eyes and when she saw the sunbeams dancing to and fro through the trees and how the ground was covered with beautiful flowers, she thought, "If a take a fresh bouquet to grandmother, she will be very pleased. Anyway, it is still early, and I'll be home on time." And she ran off the path into the woods looking for flowers. Each time she picked one she thought that she could see an even more beautiful one a little way off, and she ran after it, going further and further into the woods. But the wolf ran straight to the grandmother's house and knocked on the door.

"Who's there?"

"Little Red Cap. I'm bringing you some cake and wine. Open the door."

"Just press the latch," called out the grandmother. "I'm too weak to get up."

The wolf pressed the latch, and the door opened. He stepped inside, went straight to the grandmother's bed, and ate her up. Then he put on her clothes, put her cap on his head, got into her bed, and pulled the curtains shut.

Little Red Cap had run after the flowers. After she had gathered so many that she could not carry any more, she remembered her grandmother, and then continued on her way to her house. She found, to her surprise, that the door was open. She walked into the parlor, and everything looked so strange that she thought, "Oh, my God, why am I so afraid? I usually like it at grandmother's."

She called out, "Good morning!" but received no answer.

Then she went to the bed and pulled back the curtains. Grandmother was lying there with her cap pulled down over her face and looking very strange.

"Oh, grandmother, what big ears you have!"

"All the better to hear you with."

"Oh, grandmother, what big eyes you have!"

"All the better to see you with."

"Oh, grandmother, what big hands you have!"

"All the better to grab you with!"

"Oh, grandmother, what a horribly big mouth you have!"

"All the better to eat you with!"

The wolf had scarcely finished speaking when he jumped from the bed with a single leap and ate up poor Little Red Cap. As soon as the wolf had satisfied his desires, he climbed back into bed, fell asleep, and began to snore very loudly.

A huntsman was just passing by. He thought, "The old woman is snoring so loudly. You had better see if something is wrong with her."

He stepped into the parlor, and when he approached the bed, he saw the wolf lying there. "So here I find you, you old sinner," he said. "I have been hunting for you a long time."

He was about to aim his rifle when it occurred to him that the wolf might have eaten the grandmother, and that she still might be rescued. So instead of shooting, he took a pair of scissors and began to cut open the wolf's belly. After a few cuts he saw the red cap shining through., and after a few more cuts the girl jumped out, crying, "Oh, I was so frightened! It was so dark inside the wolf's body!"

And then the grandmothercame out as well, alive but hardly able to breathe. Then Little Red Cap fetched some large stones. She filled the wolf's body with them, and when he woke up and tried to run away, the stones were so heavy that he immediately fell down dead.

The three of them were happy. The huntsman skinned the wolf and went home with the pelt. The grandmother ate the cake and drank the wine that Little Red Cap had brought. And Little Red Cap thought, "As long as I live, I will never leave the path and run off into the woods by myself if mother tells me not to."

They also tell how Little Red Cap was taking some baked things to her grandmother another time, when another wolf spoke to her and wanted her to leave the path. But Little Red Cap took care and went straight to grandmother's. She told her that she had seen the wolf, and that he had wished her a good day, but had stared at her in a wicked manner. "If we hadn't been on a public road, he would have eaten me up," she said.

"Come," said the grandmother. "Let's lock the door, so he can't get in."

Soon afterward the wolf knocked on the door and called out, "Open up, grandmother. It's Little Red Cap, and I'm bringing you some baked things."

They remained silent, and did not open the door. Gray-Head crept around the house several times, and finally jumped onto the roof. He wanted to wait until Little Red Cap went home that evening, then follow her and eat her up in the darkness. But the grandmother saw what he was up to. There was a large stone trough in front of the house.

"Fetch a bucket, Little Red Cap," she said to the child. "Yesterday I cooked some sausage. Carry the water that I boiled them with to the trough." Little Red Cap carried water until the large, large trough was clear full. The smell of sausage arose into the wolf's nose. He sniffed and looked down, stretching his neck so long that he could no longer hold himself, and he began to slide. He slid off the roof, fell into the trough, and drowned. And Little Red Cap returned home happily, and no one harmed her.

Es war einmal eine kleine süße Dirn, die hatte jedermann lieb, der sie nur ansah, am al- lerliebsten aber ihre Großmutter, die wußte gar nicht, was sie alles dem Kind geben sollte. Ein- mal schenkte sie ihm ein Käppchen von rothem Sammet, und weil ihm das so wohl stand, und es nichts anders mehr tragen wollte, hieß es nur das Rothkäppchen; da sagte einmal seine Mutter zu ihm: „komm, Rothkäppchen, da hast du ein Stück Kuchen und ein Bouteille mit Wein, die bring der Großmutter hinaus, sie ist krank und schwach, da wird sie sich daran laben; sey hübsch artig und grüß sie von mir, geh auch ordentlich und lauf nicht vom Weg ab, sonst fällst du, und zerbrichst das Glas, dann hat die kranke Großmutter nichts.“

Rothkäppchen versprach der Mutter recht gehorsam zu seyn. Die Großmutter aber wohn- te draußen im Wald, eine halbe Stunde vom Dorf. Wie nun Rothkäppchen in den Wald kam, begegnete ihm der Wolf, Rothkäppchen aber wußte nicht, was das für ein böses Thier war, und fürchtete sich nicht vor ihm. „Guten Tag, Rothkäppchen.“ „Schön Dank Wolf.“ „Wo willst du so früh hinaus, Rothkäpp- chen,“ „zur Großmutter.“ „Was trägst du unter der Schürze?“ „die Großmutter ist krank und schwach, da bring ich ihr Kuchen und Wein, gestern haben wir gebacken, da soll sie sich stärken.“ „Rothkäppchen, wo wohnt deine Großmutter?“ „Noch eine gute Vier- telstunde im Wald, unter den drei großen Eich- bäumen, da steht ihr Haus, unten sind die Nußhecken das wirst du ja wissen“ sagte Roth- käppchen. Der Wolf gedacht bei sich, das ist ein guter fetter Bissen für mich, wie fängst dus an, daß du den kriegst: „hör Rothkäpp- chen, sagte er, hast du die schönen Blumen nicht gesehen, die im Walde stehen, warum guckst du nicht einmal um dich, ich glaube, du hörst gar nicht darauf, wie die Vöglein lieblich singen, du gehst ja für dich hin als wenn du im Dorf in die Schule gingst, und ist so lustig haußen in dem Wald.“

Rothkäppchen schlug die Augen auf, und sah wie die Sonne durch die Bäume gebrochen war und alles voll schöner Blumen stand; da gedacht es: ei! wenn ich der Großmutter einen Strauß mitbringe, der wird ihr auch lieb seyn, es ist noch früh, ich komm doch zu rechter Zeit an, und sprang in den Wald und suchte Blu- men. Und wenn es eine gebrochen hatte, meint es, dort stünd noch eine schönere und lief dar- nach und immer weiter in den Wald hinein. Der Wolf aber ging geradeswegs nach dem Haus der Großmutter und klopfte an die Thü- re. „Wer ist draußen“ „das Rothkäppchen, ich bring dir Kuchen und Wein, mach mir auf.“ „Drück nur auf die Klinke, rief die Großmutter, ich bin zu schwach und kann nicht aufstehen.“ Der Wolf drückte an der Klinke, und die Thüre sprang auf. Da ging er hin- ein, geradezu an das Bett der Großmutter und verschluckte sie. Dann nahm er ihre Kleider, that sie an, setzte sich ihre Haube auf, legte sich in ihr Bett und zog die Vorhänge vor.

Rothkäppchen aber war herum gelaufen nach Blumen, und erst als es so viel hatte, daß es keine mehr tragen konnte, machte es sich auf den Weg zu der Großmutter. Wie es ankam stand die Thüre auf, darüber verwunderte es sich, und wie es in die Stube kam, sahs so seltsam darin aus, daß es dacht: ei! du mein Gott wie ängstlich wird mirs heut zu Muth, und bin sonst so gern bei der Großmutter. Drauf ging es zum Bett und zog die Vorhänge zurück, da lag die Großmutter und hatte die Haube tief ins Gesicht gesetzt und sah so wun- derlich aus. „Ei Großmutter, was hast du für große Ohren!“ „daß ich dich besser hö- ren kann.“ „Ei Großmutter, was hast du für große Augen!“ „daß ich dich besser se- hen kann.“ „Ei Großmutter was hast du für große Hände!“ „daß ich dich besser packen kann.“ „Aber Großmutter, was hast du für ein entsetzlich großes Maul!“ „daß ich dich besser fressen kann.“ Damit sprang der Wolf aus dem Bett, sprang auf das arme Rothkäppchen, und verschlang es.

Wie der Wolf den fetten Bissen erlangt hatte, legte er sich wieder ins Bett, schlief ein und fing an, überlaut zu schnarchen. Der Jä- ger ging eben vorbei und gedacht wie kann die alte Frau so schnarchen, du mußt einmal nach- sehen. Da trat er hinein und wie er vors Bett kam, da lag der Wolf den er lange ge- sucht, der hat gewiß die Großmutter gefressen vielleicht ist sie noch zu retten, ich will nicht schießen, dachte der Jäger. Da nahm er die Scheere und schnitt ihm den Bauch auf, und wie er ein paar Schnitte gethan, da sah er das rothe Käppchen leuchten, und wie er noch ein wenig geschnitten, da sprang das Mädchen her- aus und rief: „ach wie war ich erschrocken, was wars so dunkel in dem Wolf seinem Leib;“ und dann kam die Großmutter auch lebendig heraus. Rothkäppchen aber holte große schwere Steine, damit füllten sie dem Wolf den Leib, und wie er aufwachte, wollte er fortspringen, aber die Steine waren so schwer, daß er sich todt fiel.

Da waren alle drei vergnügt, der Jäger nahm den Pelz vom Wolf, die Großmutter aßden Kuchen und trank den Wein, den Roth- käppchen gebracht hatte, und Rothkäppchen ge- dacht bei sich: du willst dein Lebtag nicht wie- der allein vom Weg ab in den Wald laufen, wenn dirs die Mutter verboten hat.

Es wird auch erzählt, daß einmal, als Roth- käppchen der alten Großmutter wieder Gebacke- nes brachte, ein anderer Wolf ihm zugesprochen und es vom Weg ableiten wollen. Rothkäpp- chen aber hütete sich und ging gerad fort ihres Wegs, und sagte der Großmutter daß sie den Wolf gesehen, daß er ihm guten Tag gewünscht aber so bös aus den Augen geguckt; „wenns nicht auf offner Straße gewesen, er hätt mich gefressen.“ „Komm, sagte die Großmutter wir wollen die Thüre verschließen, daß er nicht herein kann.“ Bald darnach klopfte der Wolf an und rief: „mach auf, Großmutter, ich bin das Rothkäppchen, ich bring dir Gebackenes.“ Sie schwiegen aber still und machten die Thüre nicht auf, da ging der Böse etlichemal um das Haus und sprang endlich aufs Dach, und wollte warten bis Rothkäppchen Abends nach Haus ging, dann wollt' er ihm nachschleichen und wollts in der Dunkelheit fressen. Aber die Großmutter merkte, was er im Sinn hatte; da stand vor dem Haus ein großer Steintrog: „hol' den Eimer, Rothkäppchen, gestern hab ich Würste gekocht, da trag das Wasser, worin sie gekocht sind, in den Trog.“ Rothkäppchen trug so lange bis der große, große Trog ganz voll war. Da stieg der Geruch von den Wür- sten dem Wolf in die Nase, er schnupperte und guckte hinab, endlich machte er den Hals so lang, daß er sich nicht mehr halten konnte, er fing an zu rutschen, und rutschte vom Dach herab und gerade in den großen Trog hinein und ertrank. Rothkäppchen aber ging fröhlich und sicher nach Haus.

Sweetheart Roland

English Version

German Version

Once upon a time there was a woman who was trulya witch. She had two daughters, one ugly and wicked, whom she loved because she was her own daughter, and one beautiful and good, whom she hated, because she was her stepdaughter. The stepdaughter had a beautiful apron, which the other girl wanted so much that she became envious, and she told her mother that she just had to have that apron. "Be still, my child," said the old woman, "and you shall have it. Your stepsister has long deserved to die, and tonight when she is asleep I will come and chop off her head. Just be sure to lie down at the far side of the bed, and push her close to the front." It would have been all over with the poor girl, but just then she was standing in a corner, and she overheard everything. She was not allowed to go outside all day long, and at bedtime her wicked stepsister had her get into bed first, so she would be lying next to the wall. However, after the witch's daughter fell asleep, the stepdaughter gently pushed her to the front side of the bed, and she took her place back against the wall. In the night the old woman crept into the bedroom holding an ax in her right hand while feeling with her left hand for anyone lying at the front of the bed. Then she grasped the axe with both hands and chopped off her own child's head.

After the witch had gone away, the girl got up and went to her sweetheart, whose name was Roland, and knocked at his door. When he came out, she said to him, "Listen, dearest Roland, we must flee at once. My stepmother tried to kill me, but she killed her own child instead. When daylight comes, and she sees what she has done, we'll be lost." "You had better take her magic wand," said Roland, "or we will not be able to escape if she comes after us." The girl got the magic wand, then she took the dead girl's head and dropped three drops of blood onto the floor, one in front of the bed, one in the kitchen, and one on the steps. Then she hurried away with her sweetheart.

The next morning when the old witch got up, she called her daughter, wanting to give her the apron. But the daughter did not come. So she shouted, "Where are you?" "Here on the steps. I'm sweeping," answered the first drop of blood. The old woman went out, but seeing no one on the steps, she shouted again, "Where are you?" "Here in the kitchen. I'm warming myself," shouted the second drop of blood. She went into the kitchen, but found no one. So she shouted again, "Where are you?" "Here in the bed. I'm sleeping," shouted the third drop of blood. She went into the bedroom and approached the bed. What did she see there? Her own child swimming in blood and whose head she herself had cut off.

The witch flew into a rage, jumped to the window, and as she could see far into the world, she saw her stepdaughter hurrying away with her sweetheart Roland. "That won't help you!" shouted the witch. "Even if you've already gone a long way, you won't escape from me!" She put on her many-league boots, in which she covered an hour's walk with every step, and it was not long before she overtook them. However, when the girl saw the old woman striding toward them, she used the magic wand to transform her sweetheart Roland into a lake, and herself into a duck swimming in the middle of the lake. The witch stood on the shore and threw in pieces of bread, trying with great effort to lure the duck to her. But the duck did not give in, and the old woman had to return home that night without success. Afterward the girl and her sweetheart Roland returned to their natural shapes, and they walked on through the whole night until daybreak.Then the girl transformed herself into a beautiful flower in the middle of a briar hedge, andher sweetheart Roland into a fiddler.

It was not long before the witch came striding up toward them. She said to the musician, "Dear musician, may I pick that beautiful flower for myself?" "Oh, yes," he replied. "And I will play for you while you're doing it." She crawled hastily into the hedge and was just about to pick the flower, knowing perfectly well who it was, when he began to play. She was forced to dance, whether she wanted to or not, for it was magic dance music. The faster he played, the more violently she was forced to jump. The thorns tore the clothes off her body, pricking her until she bled, and as he did not stop, she had to dance until she fell down dead.

They were now free, so Roland said, "Now I will go to my father and arrange for our wedding." "I'll stay here and wait for you," said the girl. "And I'll transform myself into a red boundary stone, so that no one will recognize me." So Roland set forth, and the girl, in the shape of a red boundary stone, stood there and waited for her sweetheart. But when Roland arrived home, he was snared by another woman, who caused him to forget the girl. The poor girl waited there a long time. Finally, when he failed to return, she grew sad and transformed herself into a flower, thinking, "Someone will surely come this way and trample me down."

However, it happened that a shepherd who was herding his sheep in the field saw the flower. As it was so beautiful, he picked it, took it home with him, and put it away in his chest. From that time forth, strange things happened in the shepherd's house. When he arose in the morning all the work was already done. The room was swept, the table and benches cleaned, the fire on the hearth was lighted, and the water was fetched, and at noon, when he came home, the table was already set, and a good dinner served. He didn't know how this happened, for he never saw anyone in his house, and no one could have hidden himself in it. He was, of course, pleased with this good service, but with time he became so afraid that he went to a wise woman and asked for her advice. The wise woman said, "There is magic behind it. Be on the watch very early some morning, and if anything is moving in the room, if you see anything, no matter what it is, throw a white cloth over it, and then the magic will be stopped."

The shepherd did what she told him to do, and the next morning just at dawn, he saw the chest open and the flower come out. He quickly jumped towards it and threw a white cloth over it. Instantly the transformation came to an end, and a beautiful girl stood before him, who admitted to him that she had been the flower, and that she had been doing his housekeeping. She told him her story. He liked her and asked her to marry him, but she answered, "No," for she wanted to remain faithful to her sweetheart Roland, even though he had abandoned her. Nevertheless, she promised not to go away, and to continue keeping house for the shepherd. The time drew near when Roland was to be married. According to an old custom in that country, it was announced that all the girls were to attend the wedding and sing in honor of the bridal pair. When the faithful girl heard this, she grew so sad that she thought her heart would break, and she did not want to go. But the other girls came and took her. When it was her turn to sing, she declined, until at last she was the only one left, and then she could not refuse. But when she began her song, and it reached Roland's ears, he jumped up and shouted, "I know that voice. That is the true bride. I do not want anyone else." Everything he had forgotten, and which had vanished from his mind, had suddenly come home again to his heart. Thus the faithful girl was married to her sweetheart Roland. Her grief came to an end, and her joy began.

Es war einmal eine Mutter, die hatte nur ihre rechte Tochter lieb und haßte ihre Stief- tochter, die doch tausendmal schöner und besser war. Einmal hatte diese eine schöne Schürze, darüber war die andere neidisch und verlangte von der Mutter, sie solle ihr diese Schürze verschaffen. Die Mutter sagte: „sey still, mein liebes Kind, du sollst sie haben, deine Stief- schwester hat doch schon lange den Tod ver- dient, heut Nacht leg dich hinten ins Bett und schieb sie recht vorne hin, dann will ich kom- men, wenn sie schläft, und will ihr den Kopf abhauen.“ Die Stiefschwester aber hatte in einer Ecke gestanden und alles mit angehört, da ließ sie die böse Schwester erst zu Bett ge- hen, daß sie hinten hin kam, wie sie aber ein- geschlafen war, hub sie sie auf und legte sie vorne hin, sich aber ganz hinten. Da kam die Mutter in der Nacht geschlichen, fühlte erst ob vorne jemand lag und schlief, dann faßte sie die Axt mit beiden Händen und hieb und hieb ihrem eigenen Kind den Kopf ab.

Wie sie fortgegangen war, stand das Mäd- chen auf und ging zu seinem Liebsten Roland, klopfte an und rief: „hör, wir müssen fort, die Stiefmutter hat ihr eigen Kind todtgeschlagen, und meint sie hätte mich getroffen, kommt der Tag und sie sieht, was sie gethan, so bin ich verloren; da hab ich ihren Zauberstab genom- men, damit können wir uns schon helfen.“ Der Liebste Roland stand auf, und sie nahmen erst den todten Kopf und tröpfelten drei Bluts- tropfen, einen vors Bett, einen in die Küche und einen auf die Treppe; darauf gingen sie fort. Am Morgen, als die Mutter aufgestan- den war, rief sie ihrer Tochter: „komm, du sollst jetzt die Schürze haben,“ die Tochter kam aber nicht. „Wo bist du?“ „Ei! hier auf der Treppe, die kehr ich,“ sprach der eine Blutstropfen. Da ging sie hinaus; auf der Treppe war niemand: „wo bist du denn?“ „Ei! hier in der Küche, beim Feuer, da wärm ich mich!“ rief der zweite Blutstropfen; sie ging in die Küche, aber sie sah niemand: „wo bist du denn aber?“ „Ach! hier am Bett, da schlaf ich!“ sie lief in die Kammer ans Bett, da sah sie ihr eigen Kind in seinem Blu- te schwimmen. Da erschrack sie und merkte, daß sie betrogen war, und ward zornig, weil sie aber eine Hexe war, konnte sie weit in die Welt hineinsehen, und sah ihre Stieftochter mit ihren Liebsten forteilen, und sie waren schon weit weg. Alsbald zog sie ihre Meilenstiefeln an, und ging ihnen nach, hatte sie auch bald eingeholt; das Mädchen aber hatte durch den Zauberstab gewußt, daß sie verfolgt würden, und sich in einen See, ihren Liebsten Roland aber in eine Ente verwandelt, die schwamm darauf. Als nun die Stiefmutter herzu kam, setzte sie sich an das Ufer und suchte die Ente mit Brod zu locken, aber es war alle Mühe ver- geblich, am Abend mußte sie unverrichteter Sa- che heimgehen. Die zwei nahmen ihre mensch- liche Gestalt wieder an, und gingen weiter, wie aber der Tag anbrach wurden sie wieder von der Hexe verfolgt. Da verwandelte sich das Mädchen in eine schöne Blume, die mitten in einer Dornhecke stand, ihren Liebsten Roland aber in einen Geigenspieler. Wie die Alte an- kam, fragte sie den Spielmann, ob sie sich die Blume abbrechen dürfe, „o ja, antwortete der, nur will ich dazu aufspielen.“ Da kroch sie in die Hecke und suchte zu der Blume zu reichen; wie sie aber mitten darin war, fing er an zu spielen, und da mußte sie darnach tanzen und tanzen ohne Aufhören, daß ihr die Dornen die Kleider vom Leibe rissen und sie blutig stachen, so lang, bis sie todt hinfiel.

Da waren beide frei. Roland aber sprach zu dem Mädchen: „nun will ich heim gehen zu meinem Vater, und die Hochzeit bestellen.“ „Da will ich mich indessen in einen rothen Feld- stein verwandeln, und hier bleiben und warten, bis du wieder kommst.“ Da stand es als ein rother Stein und wartete lang auf seinen Lieb- sten, aber der kam nicht wieder und hatte sie vergessen, und als er gar nicht kommen wollte, ward es ganz traurig und verwandelte sich in eine Blume, und dachte, es wird mich ja bald jemand umtreten. Ein Schäfer aber fand die Blume, und weil sie so schön war, nahm er sie mit sich, und legte sie daheim in seinen Ka- sten. Von nun an aber ging es wunderlich bei dem Schäfer zu: wenn er des Morgens aufwachte, so war alles im Haus gethan, ge- kehrt, geputzt, Feuer angemacht, und kam er Mittags nach Haus, war das Essen gekocht, der Tisch gedeckt und aufgetragen; er konnte aber nicht begreifen, wie das zuging, sah auch niemals einen Menschen in seinem Haus. Und ob es ihm gleich wohl gefiel, so ward ihm doch zuletzt Angst dabei, und er fragte eine weise Frau darüber, die sagte, das sey Zauberei, er solle einmal Morgens früh Acht geben, ob sich etwas in der Stube bewege, und wenn er et- was sehe ein weißes Tuch darüber werfen. Das that er, und am andern Morgen sah er, wie sich der Kasten aufthat und die Blume her- auskam, er sprang herzu und warf ein Tuch darüber, da war die Verwandlung vorbei, und das schöne Mädchen, das sein Liebster Roland vergessen hat, stand vor ihm. Der Schäfer wollte es heirathen, es sagte aber nein, es wolle ihm nur dienen und haushalten. Bald darauf hörte es, daß Roland Hochzeit halten und eine andere heirathen wolle; dabei mußte jeder im Land nach einem alten Gebrauch, sin- gen. Da kam das treue Mädchen auch hin, und wollte immer nicht singen, bis zu allerletzt, da mußte es; wie es aber anfing, da erkannte es Roland gleich, sprang auf und sagte: das sey seine rechte Braut, er wolle keine andere und vermählte sich mir ihr; da war sein Leid zu End und seine Freude ging an.

The Six Swans

English Version

German Version

A king was once hunting in a great forest, and he chased his prey so eagerly that none of his men could follow him. As evening approached he stopped and looked around, and saw that he was lost. He looked for a way out of the woods, but he could not find one. Then he saw an old woman with a bobbing head who approached him. She was a witch.

"My dear woman," he said to her, "can you show me the way through the woods?"

"Oh, yes, your majesty," she answered, "I can indeed. However, there is one condition, and if you do not fulfill it, you will never get out of these woods, and will die here of hunger."

"What sort of condition is it?" asked the king.

"I have a daughter," said the old woman, who is as beautiful as anyone you could find in all the world, and who well deserves to become your wife. If you will make her your queen, I will show you the way out of the woods."

The king was so frightened that he consented, and the old woman led him to her cottage, where her daughter was sitting by the fire. She received the king as if she had been expecting him. He saw that she was very beautiful, but in spite of this he did not like her, and he could not look at her without secretly shuddering.

After he had lifted the girl onto his horse, the old woman showed him the way, and the king arrived again at his royal castle, where the wedding was celebrated.

The king had been married before, and by his first wife he had seven children, six boys and one girl. He loved them more than anything else in the world.

Fearing that the stepmother might not treat them well, even do them harm, he took them to a secluded castle which stood in the middle of a forest. It was so well hidden, and the way was so difficult to find, that he himself would not have found it, if a wise woman had not given him a ball of magic yarn. Whenever he threw it down in front of him, it would unwind itself and show him the way.

However, the king went out to his dear children so often that the queen took notice of his absence. She was curious and wanted to know what he was doing out there all alone in the woods. She gave a large sum of money to his servants, and they revealed the secret to her. They also told her about the ball of yarn which could point out the way all by itself.

She did not rest until she discovered where the king kept the ball of yarn. Then she made some little shirts of white silk. Having learned the art of witchcraft from her mother, she sewed a magic charm into each one of them. Then one day when the king had ridden out hunting, she took the little shirts and went into the woods. The ball of yarn showed her the way.

The children, seeing that someone was approaching from afar, thought that their dear father was coming to them. Full of joy, they ran to meet him. Then she threw one of the shirts over each of them, and when the shirts touched their bodies they were transformed into swans, and they flew away over the woods.

The queen went home very pleased, believing that she had gotten rid of her stepchildren. However, the girl had not run out with her brothers, and the queen knew nothing about her.

The next day the king went to visit his children, but he found no one there but the girl.

"Where are your brothers?" asked the king.

"Oh, dear father," she answered, "they have gone away and left me alone."

Then she told him that from her window she had seen how her brothers had flown away over the woods as swans. She showed him the feathers that they had dropped into the courtyard, and which she had gathered up.

The king mourned, but he did not think that the queen had done this wicked deed. Fearing that the girl would be stolen away from him as well, he wanted to take her away with him, but she was afraid of her stepmother and begged the king to let her stay just this one more night in the castle in the woods.

The poor girl thought, "I can no longer stay here. I will go and look for my brothers."

And when night came she ran away and went straight into the woods. She walked the whole night long without stopping, and the next day as well, until she was too tired to walk any further.

Then she saw a hunter's hut and went inside. She found a room with six little beds, but she did not dare to get into one of them. Instead she crawled under one of them and lay down on the hard ground where she intended to spend the night.

The sun was about to go down when she heard a rushing sound and saw six swans fly in through the window. Landing on the floor, they blew on one another, and blew all their feathers off. Then their swan-skins came off just like shirts. The girl looked at them and recognized her brothers. She was happy and crawled out from beneath the bed. The brothers were no less happy to see their little sister, but their happiness did not last long.

"You cannot stay here," they said to her. "This is a robbers' den. If they come home and find you, they will murder you."

"Can't you protect me?" asked the little sister.

"No," they answered. "We can take off our swan-skins for only a quarter hour each evening. Only during that time do we have our human forms. After that we are again transformed into swans."

Crying, the little sister said, "Can you not be redeemed?"

"Alas, no," they answered. "The conditions are too difficult. You would not be allowed to speak or to laugh for six years, and in that time you would have to sew together six little shirts from asters for us. And if a single word were to come from your mouth, all your work would be lost."

After the brothers had said this, the quarter hour was over, and they flew out the window again as swans.

Nevertheless, the girl firmly resolved to redeem her brothers, even if it should cost her her life. She left the hunter's hut, went to the middle of the woods, seated herself in a tree, and there spent the night. The next morning she went out and gathered asters and began to sew. She could not speak with anyone, and she had no desire to laugh. She sat there, looking only at her work.

After she had already spent a long time there it happened that the king of the land was hunting in these woods. His huntsmen came to the tree where the girl was sitting.

They called to her, saying, "Who are you?" But she did not answer.

"Come down to us," they said. "We will not harm you."

She only shook her head. When they pressed her further with questions, she threw her golden necklace down to them, thinking that this would satisfy them. But they did not stop, so she then threw her belt down to them, and when this did not help, her garters, and then -- one thing at a time -- everything that she had on and could do without, until finally she had nothing left but her shift.

The huntsmen, however, not letting themselves be dissuaded, climbed the tree, lifted the girl down, and took her to the king.

The king asked, "Who are you? What are you doing in that tree?"

But she did not answer. He asked her in every language that he knew, but she remained as speechless as a fish. Because she was so beautiful, the king's heart was touched, and he fell deeply in love with her. He put his cloak around her, lifted her onto his horse in front of himself, and took her to his castle. There he had her dressed in rich garments, and she glistened in her beauty like bright daylight, but no one could get a word from her.

At the table he seated her by his side, and her modest manners and courtesy pleased him so much that he said, "My desire is to marry her, and no one else in the world."

A few days later they were married.

Now the king had a wicked mother who was dissatisfied with this marriage and spoke ill of the young queen. "Who knows," she said, "where the girl who cannot speak comes from? She is not worthy of a king."

A year later, after the queen had brought her first child into the world, the old woman took it away from her while she was asleep, and smeared her mouth with blood. Then she went to the king and accused her of being a cannibal. The king could not believe this, and would not allow anyone to harm her. She, however, sat the whole time sewing on the shirts, and caring for nothing else.

The next time, when she again gave birth to a beautiful boy, the deceitful mother-in-law did the same thing again, but the king could not bring himself to believe her accusations.

He said, "She is too pious and good to do anything like that. If she were not speechless, and if she could defend herself, her innocence would come to light."

But when the old woman stole away a newly born child for the third time, and accused the queen, who did not defend herself with a single word, the king had no choice but to bring her to justice, and she was sentenced to die by fire.

When the day came for the sentence to be carried out, it was also the last day of the six years during which she had not been permitted to speak or to laugh, and she had thus delivered her dear brothers from the magic curse. The six shirts were finished. Only the left sleeve of the last one was missing. When she was led to the stake, she laid the shirts on her arm. Standing there, as the fire was about to be lighted, she looked around, and six swans came flying through the air. Seeing that their redemption was near, her heart leapt with joy.

The swans rushed towards her, swooping down so that she could throw the shirts over them. As soon as the shirts touched them their swan-skins fell off, and her brothers stood before her in their own bodies, vigorous and handsome. However, the youngest was missing his left arm. In its place he had a swan's wing.

They embraced and kissed one another. Then the queen went to the king, who was greatly moved, and she began to speak, saying, "Dearest husband, now I may speak and reveal to you that I am innocent, and falsely accused."

Then she told him of the treachery of the old woman who had taken away their three children and hidden them.

Then to the king's great joy they were brought forth. As a punishment, the wicked mother-in-law was tied to the stake and burned to ashes. But the king and the queen with her six brothers lived many long years in happiness and peace.

Ein König jagte in einem großen Wald, verirrte sich und konnte keinen Ausgang finden, da kam er endlich zu einer Hexe, die bat er, sie mögte ihn wieder heraus leiten. Die Hexe aber antwortete, das geschähe nimmermehr, er müsse darin bleiben und sein Leben verlieren, und nur das eine könne ihn erretten, daß er ihre Tochter heirathe. Dem König war sein Leben lieb, und in der Angst sagte er ja; die Hexe brachte ihm das Mädchen, es war jung und schön, er konnte es aber nicht ohne Grau- sen und ohne eine heimliche Furcht ansehen; doch wollte er, was er versprochen hatte, hal- ten. Die Alte führte dann beide auf den rech- ten Weg, und daheim ward die Hexentochter seine Gemahlin. Der König aber hatte noch sieben Kinder von seiner ersten Frau, sechs Buben und ein Mädchen, und weil er fürch- tete, es könne ihnen von der Stiefmutter ein Leids angethan werden, brachte er sie in ein Schloß, das er mitten in einem Walde stehen hatte. Es stand so verborgen, daß niemand den Weg dahin wußte, und er selber hätte ihn nicht gefunden, wenn ihm nicht eine weise Frau einen Knauel von Garn gegeben, wenn er den vor sich warf, wickelte er sich auf und zeigte ihm den Weg. Weil aber der König seine Kin- der gar lieb hatte, ging er oft hinaus, da ward die Königin neugierig, und wollte wissen, was der König so viel allein in dem Wald zu thun habe; sie forschte die Diener aus, und diese ver- riethen ihr das ganze Geheimniß. Das erste war nun, daß sie sich mit List den Knauel ver- schaffte, dann nahm sie sieben kleine Hemdchen, und ging hinaus in den Wald. Der Knauel zeigte ihr den Weg, und als die sechs kleinen Prinzen sie von weitem kommen sahen, freuten sie sich, meinten ihr Vater käm und liefen her- aus auf sie zu. Da warf sie über jeden ein Hemdchen, und kaum hatte es ihren Leib be- rührt, da waren sie in Schwäne verwandelt, hoben sich auf in die Luft und flogen davon. Sie meinte nun sie hätte alle Stiefkinder weg- geschafft, und ging wieder heim, und so war das Mädchen, das in seiner Kammer geblieben war, errettet. Am andern Tag kam der König in das Waldschloß, da erzählte es ihm, was ge- schehen war, und zeigte ihm noch die Schwa- nenfedern, die von ihren sechs Brüdern auf den Hof gefallen waren. Der König erschrack, gedachte aber nimmermehr, daß die Königin die böse That vollbracht, und weil er besorgte, die Prinzessin möge ihm auch geraubt werden, wollte er sie mit sich nach Haus nehmen. Sie fürchtete sich aber vor ihrer Stiefmutter und bat ihn, er mögte sie nur noch die Nacht in dem Schloß lassen; in der Nacht aber entfloh sie, und gerade zu in den Wald hinein.

Als sie auch den ganzen Tag bis zum Abend fortgegangen war, kam sie zu einer Wild- hütte. Sie stieg hinauf und fand eine Stube mit sechs kleinen Betten; weil sie nun müde war, legte sie sich unter eins und wollte da die Nacht zubringen. Bei Sonnenuntergang aber kamen sechs Schwäne durch das Fenster herein- geflogen, setzten sich auf den Boden und bliesen einander an, und bliesen sich alle Federn ab, wie ein Tuch sich abstreift, und da waren es ihre sechs Brüder. Sie kroch unter dem Bett hervor, und die Brüder waren beides erfreut und betrübt, sie zu sehen: „du kannst hier nicht bleiben, sagten sie, das ist eine Räuberherberg, wenn die Räuber von ihrem Zuge heimkom- men, dann wohnen sie hier. Alle Abend kön- nen wir uns aber eine Viertelstunde lang die Schwanenhaut gänzlich abblasen, und auf so lange unsere menschliche Gestalt haben, hernach aber ist es wieder vorbei. Wenn du uns erlösen willst, mußt du in sechs Jahren sechs Hemd- lein aus Sternblumen zusammennähen, wäh- rend der Zeit aber darfst du nicht sprechen und nicht lachen, sonst ist alle Arbeit verloren.“ Und als die Brüder das gesprochen hatten, war die Viertelstunde herum, und sie waren wieder in Schwäne verwandelt.

Am andern Morgen aber sammelte sich das Mädchen Sternblumen, setzte sich dann auf einen hohen Baum und fing an zu nähen: es redete auch kein Wort und lachte nicht, sondern sahe nur auf seine Arbeit. Auf eine Zeit jagte der König, dem das Land gehörte in dem Wald, und seine Jäger kamen zu dem Baum, auf welchem es saß. Sie riefen ihm zu, es sollte herabsteigen, weil es ihnen nun nicht antwor- ten durfte, wollte es sie mit Geschenken befrie- digen, und warf ihnen seine goldene Halskette herab. Sie riefen aber noch immer, da warf es seinen Gürtel, als auch dies nichts half sei- ne Strumpfbänder endlich, alles, was es ent- behren konnte, herunter, so daß es nichts mehr als sein Hemdlein anbehielt. Den Jägern war aber das alles nicht genug, sie stiegen auf den Baum, hoben es herab und brachten es mir Gewalt zum König. Der König war verwun- dert über seine Schönheit, wickelte es in seinen Mantel, setzte es vor sich aufs Pferd, und führte es nach Haus, und ob es gleich stumm war, liebte er es doch von Herzen, und es ward seine Gemahlin. Des Königs Mutter aber war böse darüber, sprach schlecht von ihr: niemand wisse, woher die Dirne gekommen, und sie sey des Königs unwerth. Als sie nun den ersten Prinzen zur Welt brachte, nahm die Schwiegermutter ihn weg, bestrich ihr den Mund mit Blut und gab dann bei dem König vor, die Königin habe ihr eigen Kind gefressen, und sey eine Zauberin. Der König aber, aus großer Liebe, wollte es nicht glauben; darnach als sie den zweiten Prinzen gebar, übte die gottlose Schwiegermutter denselben Betrug, und klagte sie wieder beim König an, und weil sie nicht reden durfte, sondern immer stumm saß und an den sechs Hemdern arbeitete, so konnte sie nichts mehr erretten, und sie ward zum Feuer verdammt. Der Tag kam heran, wo das Urtheil sollte vollzogen werden, es war gerade der letzte Tag von den sechs Jahren, und sie war mit den sechs Hemdern fertig geworden, nur an einem fehlte der linke Ermel. Wie sie nun zum Scheiterhaufen geführt wurde, nahm sie die sechs Hemder mit sich, und wie sie oben stand und eben das Feuer sollte angesteckt wer- den, sah sie sechs Schwäne durch die Luft da- her ziehen, und über ihr sich herabsenken. Da warf sie die Hemdlein hinauf, die fielen über die Schwäne hin, und kaum waren sie davon berührt, so fiel ihre Schwanenhaut ab, und die sechs Brüder standen leibhaftig vor ihr, nur dem sechsten fehlte der linke Arm, und er hatte dafür einen Schwanenflügel auf dem Rücken. Da war ihr auch die Sprache wiedergegeben, und sie erzählte, wie die Schwiegermutter sie so boshaft verläumdet, dafür ward diese auf den Scheiterhaufen gebracht und verbrannt, sie aber lebte lange mit dem König und ihren sechs Brüdern in Freuden.

Little Snow-White

English Version

German Version

Once upon a time in midwinter, when the snowflakes were falling like feathers from heaven,aqueen sat sewing at her window,which had a frame of black ebony wood.As she sewed she looked up at the snowandpricked her finger with her needle.Three drops of blood fell into the snow. The red on the white looked so beautiful thatshe thought to herself"If only I had a child as white as snow, as red as blood,and as black as the wood in this frame."Soon afterwardshe had a little daughterwho was as white as snow, as red as blood, and as black as ebony wood, and therefore they called herLittle Snow-White.And as soon as the child wasborn, the queen died.

A year laterthe king took himself anotherwife. She was a beautiful woman,butshe was proud and arrogant,andshe could not stand it if anyone might surpass her in beauty. She had amagic mirror. Every morningshe stood before it,looked at herself,and said:Mirror, mirror, on the wall, Who in this land is fairest of all?To this themirroranswered:You, myqueen,are fairest of all.Then she was satisfied,forshe knew that the mirror spoke the truth.

Snow-Whitegrew up and became ever more beautiful.When she was seven years old she was as beautiful as the light of day, even more beautiful than thequeenherself. One day whenthe queen asked her mirror:Mirror, mirror, on the wall, Who in this land is fairest of all?It answered:You, my queen, are fair; it is true. But Snow-White is a thousand times fairer than you.The queentook frightand turned yellow and green with envy. From that hour on whenever she looked at Snow-White her heart turned over inside her body,so great was her hatred for the girl.The envy and pride grew ever greater, like a weed in her heart, untilshe had no peace day and night.

Thenshe summoned a huntsmanand said to him,Take Snow-White out into the woods. I never want to see her again. Kill her, and as proof that she is dead bring her lungs and her liver back to me." The huntsman obeyed and took Snow-White into the woods. He took out his hunting knife and was about to stabit into her innocent heartwhen she began to cry,saying,"Oh, dear huntsman, let me live. I will run into the wild woods and never come back."Because she was so beautiful the huntsman took pity on her, and he said,"Run away, you poor child."He thought, "The wild animals will soon devour you anyway," but still it was as if a stone had fallen from his heart, for he would not have to kill her. Just then a young boar came running by. He killed it, cut out its lungs and liver, and took them back to the queen as proof of Snow-White's death. The cook had to boil them with salt, and the wicked woman ate them, supposing that she had eaten Snow-White's lungs and liver.

The poor child was now all alone in the great forest, and she was so afraid that she just looked at all the leaves on the trees and did not know what to do.Then she began to run. She ran over sharp stones and through thorns, andwild animals jumped at her, but they did her no harm. She ran as far as her feet could carry her, and just as evening was about to fall she saw a little house and went inside in order to rest. Inside the house everything was small, but so neat and clean that no one could say otherwise. There was a little table with a white tablecloth and seven little plates, and each plate had a spoon, and there were seven knives and forks and seven mugs as well. Against the wall there were seven little beds, all standing in a row and covered with snow-white sheets. Because she was so hungry and thirsty Snow-White ate a few vegetables and a little bread from each little plate, and from each mug she drank a drop of wine. Afterward, because she was so tired, she lay down on a bed, but none of them felt right -- one was too long, the other too short -- until finally the seventh one was just right. She remained lying in it, entrusted herself to God, and fell asleep.

After dark the masters of the house returned home. They were the seven dwarfs who picked and dug for ore in the mountains. They lit their seven candles, and as soon as it was light in their house they saw that someone had been there, for not everything was in the same order as they had left it. The first one said,"Who has been sitting in my chair?" The second one,"Who has been eating from my plate?"The third one,"Who has been eating my bread?"The fourth one,"Who has been eating my vegetables?"The fifth one,"Who has been sticking with my fork?"The sixth one,"Who has been cutting with my knife?"The seventh one,"Who has been drinking from my mug?"Then the first one saw a that there was a little imprint in his bed, and said,"Who stepped on my bed?"The others came running up and shouted,"Someone has been lying in mine as well."But the seventh one, looking at his bed, found Snow-White lying there asleep. The seven dwarfs all came running up, and they cried out with amazement. They fetched their seven candles and shone the light on Snow-White."Oh good heaven! Oh good heaven!"they cried."This child is so beautiful!"They were so happy, that they did not wake her up, but let her continue to sleep there in the bed. The seventh dwarf had to sleep with his companions, one hour with each one, and then the night was done.

The next morning Snow-White woke up, and when she saw the seven dwarfs she was frightened. But they were friendly and asked, "What is your name?" "My name is Snow-White," she answered. "How did you find your way to our house?"the dwarfs asked further. Then she told them that her stepmother had tried to kill her,that the huntsman had spared her life, and that she had run the entire day, finally coming to their house. The dwarfs said, "If you will keep house for us, and cook, make beds, wash, sew, and knit, and keep everything clean and orderly, then you can stay with us, and you shall have everything that you want." "Yes," said Snow-White, "with all my heart."So she kept house for them. Every morning they went into the mountains looking for ore and gold, and in the evening when they came back home their meal had to be ready. During the day the girl was alone. The good dwarfs warned her, saying, "Be careful about your stepmother. She will soon know that you are here. Do not let anyone in."

Now the queen, believing that she had eaten Snow-White 's lungs and liver, could only think that she was again the first and the most beautiful woman of all. She stepped before her mirror and said:Mirror, mirror, on the wall, Who in this land is fairest of all?It answered:You, my queen, are fair; it is true. But Snow-White, beyond the mountains With the seven dwarfs, Is still a thousand times fairer than you. This startled the queen, for she knew that the mirror did not lie, and she realized thatthe huntsman had deceived her, and that Snow-White was still alive. Then she thought, and thought again, how she could kill Snow-White, for as long as long as she was not the most beautiful woman in the entire land her envy would give her no rest.

At last she thought of something. Coloring her face,she disguised herself as an old peddler woman,so that no one would recognize her. In this disguise she went to the house of the seven dwarfs. Knocking on the door she called out,"Beautiful wares for sale, for sale!"Snow-White peered out the window and said,"Good day, dear woman, what do you have for sale?""Good wares, beautiful wares," she answered. "Bodice laces in all colors."And she took out one that was braided from colorful silk."Would you like this one?" "I can let that honest woman in," thought Snow-White,then unbolted the door and bought the pretty bodice lace."Child," said the old woman, "how you look! Come, let me lace you up properly."The unsuspecting Snow-White stood before her and let her do up the new lace, but the old woman pulled so quickly and so hard that Snow-White could not breathe. "You used to be the most beautiful one," said the old woman,and hurried away.

Not long afterward, in the evening time, the seven dwarfs came home. How terrified they were when they saw their dearSnow-White lying on the ground, not moving at all, as though she were dead. They lifted her up, and, seeing that she was too tightly laced, they cut the lace in two. Then she began to breathe a little, and little by little she came back to life.When the dwarfs heard what had happened they said, "The old peddler woman was no one else but the godless queen. Take care and let no one in when we are not with you."

When the wicked woman returned home she went to her mirror and asked: Mirror, mirror, on the wall, Who in this land is fairest of all? The mirror answered once again: You, my queen, are fair; it is true. But Snow-White, beyond the mountains With the seven dwarfs, Is still a thousand times fairer than you. When she heard that, all her blood ran to her heart because she knew that Snow-White had come back to life. "This time," she said, "I shall think of something that will destroy you."

Then with the art of witchcraft, which she understood, she made a poisoned comb. Then she disguised herself, taking the form of a different old woman. Thus she went across the seven mountains to the seven dwarfs, knocked on the door, and called out, "Good wares for sale, for sale!" Snow-White looked out and said, "Go on your way. I am not allowed to let anyone in." "You surely may take a look," said the old woman, pulling out the poisoned comb and holding it up. The child liked it so much that she let herself be deceived, and she opened the door. After they had agreed on the purchase, the old woman said, "Now let me comb your hair properly." She had barely stuck the comb into Snow-White's hair when the poison took effect, and the girl fell down unconscious. "You specimen of beauty," said the wicked woman, "now you are finished." And she walked away.

Fortunately it was almost evening, and the seven dwarfs came home. When they saw Snow-White lying on the ground as if she were dead, they immediately suspected her stepmother. They examined her and found the poisoned comb. They had scarcely pulled it out when Snow-White came to herself again and told them what had happened. Once again they warned her to be on guard and not to open the door for anyone.

Back at home the queen stepped before her mirror and said: Mirror, mirror, on the wall, Who in this land is fairest of all? The mirror answered: You, my queen, are fair; it is true. But Snow-White, beyond the mountains With the seven dwarfs, Is still a thousand times fairer than you. When the queen heard the mirror saying this, she shook and trembled with anger, "Snow-White shall die," she shouted, "if it costs me my life!"

Then she went into her most secret room -- no one else was allowed inside -- and she made a poisoned, poisoned apple. From the outside it was beautiful, white with red cheeks, and anyone who saw it would want it. But anyone who might eat a little piece of it would died. Then, coloring her face, she disguised herself as a peasant woman, and thus went across the seven mountains to the seven dwarfs. She knocked on the door. Snow-White stuck her head out the window and said, "I am not allowed to let anyone in. The dwarfs have forbidden me to do so." "That is all right with me," answered the peasant woman. "I'll easily get rid of my apples. Here, I'll give you one of them." "No," said Snow-White, "I cannot accept anything." "Are you afraid of poison?" asked the old woman. "Look, I'll cut the apple in two. You eat the red half, and I shall eat the white half." Now the apple had been so artfully made that only the red half was poisoned. Snow-White longed for the beautiful apple, and when she saw that the peasant woman was eating part of it she could no longer resist, and she stuck her hand out and took the poisoned half. She barely had a bite in her mouth when she fell to the ground dead. The queen looked at her with a gruesome stare, laughed loudly, and said, "White as snow, red as blood, black as ebony wood! This time the dwarfs cannot awaken you."

Back at home she asked her mirror: Mirror, mirror, on the wall, Who in this land is fairest of all? It finally answered: You, my queen, are fairest of all. Then her envious heart was at rest, as well as an envious heart can be at rest.

When the dwarfs came home that evening they found Snow-White lying on the ground. She was not breathing at all. She was dead. They lifted her up and looked for something poisonous. They undid her laces. They combed her hair. They washed her with water and wine. But nothing helped. The dear child was dead, and she remained dead. They laid her on a bier, and all seven sat next to her and mourned for her and cried for three days. They were going to bury her, but she still looked as fresh as a living person, and still had her beautiful red cheeks. They said, "We cannot bury her in the black earth," and they had a transparent glass coffin made, so she could be seen from all sides. They laid her inside, and with golden letters wrote on it her name, and that she was a princess. Then they put the coffin outside on a mountain, and one of them always stayed with it and watched over her. The animals too came and mourned for Snow-white, first an owl, then a raven, and finally a dove. Snow-White lay there in the coffin a long, long time, and she did not decay, but looked like she was asleep, for she was still as white as snow and as red as blood, and as black-haired as ebony wood.

Now it came to pass that a prince entered these woods and happened onto the dwarfs' house, where he sought shelter for the night. He saw the coffin on the mountain with beautiful Snow-White in it, and he read what was written on it with golden letters. Then he said to the dwarfs, "Let me have the coffin. I will give you anything you want for it." But the dwarfs answered,"We will not sell it for all the gold in the world." Then he said, "Then give it to me, for I cannot live without being able to see Snow-White. I will honor her and respect her as my most cherished one."As he thus spoke, the good dwarfs felt pity for him and gave him the coffin. The prince had his servants carry it away on their shoulders. But then it happened that one of them stumbled on some brush, and this dislodged from Snow-White's throat the piece of poisoned apple that she had bitten off. Not long afterward she opened her eyes, lifted the lid from her coffin, sat up, and was alive again. "Good heavens, where am I?" she cried out. The prince said joyfully, "You are with me." He told her what had happened, and then said, "I love you more than anything else in the world. Come with me to my father's castle. You shall become my wife."Snow White loved him, and she went with him. Their wedding was planned with great splendor and majesty.

Snow-White'sgodless stepmother was also invited to the feast. After putting on her beautiful clothes she stepped before her mirror and said: Mirror, mirror, on the wall, Who in this land is fairest of all? The mirror answered: You, my queen, are fair; it is true. But the young queen is a thousand times fairer than you. The wicked woman uttered a curse, and she became so frightened, so frightened, that she did not know what to do. At first she did not want to go to the wedding, but she found no peace. She had to go and see the young queen. When she arrived she recognized Snow-White, and terrorized, she could only stand there without moving. Then they put a pair of iron shoes into burning coals. They were brought forth with tongs and placed before her. She was forced to step into the red-hot shoes and dance until she fell down dead.

Es war einmal mitten im Winter, und die Schneeflocken fielen wie Federn vom Himmel, da saß eine schöne Königin an einem Fenster, das hatte einen Rahmen von schwarzem Eben- holz, und nähte. Und wie sie so nähte und nach dem Schnee aufblickte, stach sie sich mit der Nadel in den Finger, und es fielen drei Tropfen Blut in den Schnee. Und weil das Rothe in dem Weißen so schön aussah, so dach- te sie: hätt ich doch ein Kind so weiß wie Schnee, so roth wie Blut und so schwarz wie dieser Rahmen. Und bald darauf bekam sie ein Töchterlein, so weiß wie der Schnee, so roth wie das Blut, und so schwarz wie Eben- holz, und darum ward es das Sneewittchen ge- nannt.

Die Königin war die schönste im ganzen Land, und gar stolz auf ihre Schönheit. Sie hatte auch einen Spiegel, vor den trat sie alle Morgen und fragte: „Spieglein, Spieglein an der Wand: wer ist die schönste Frau in dem ganzen Land?“ da sprach das Spieglein allzeit: „Ihr, Frau Königin, seyd die schönste Frau im Land.“ heran, und als es sieben Jahr alt war, war es so schön, daß es selbst die Königin an Schön- heit übertraf, und als diese ihren Spiegel fragte: „Spieglein, Spieglein an der Wand: wer ist die schönste Frau in dem ganzen Land?“ sagte der Spiegel: „Frau Königin, Ihr seyd die schönste hier, aber Snewittchen ist noch tausendmal schöner als Ihr!“ Wie die Königin den Spiegel so sprechen hör- te, ward sie blaß vor Neid, und von Stund an haßte sie das Sneewittchen, und wenn sie es ansah, und gedacht, daß durch seine Schuld sie nicht mehr die schönste auf der Welt sey, kehrte sich ihr das Herz herum. Da ließ ihr der Neid keine Ruhe, und sie rief einen Jäger und sagte zu ihm: „führ das Sneewittchen hinaus in den Wald an einen weiten abgelege- nen Ort, da stichs todt, und zum Wahrzeichen bring mir seine Lunge und seine Leber mit, die will ich mit Salz kochen und essen.“ Der Jä- ger nahm das Sneewittchen und führte es hin- aus, wie er aber den Hirschfänger gezogen hat- te und eben zustechen wollte, da fing es an zu weinen, und bat so sehr, er mögt ihm sein Le- ben lassen, es wollt nimmermehr zurückkom- men, sondern in dem Wald fortlaufen. Den Jäger erbarmte es, weil es so schön war und gedachte: die wilden Thiere werden es doch bald gefressen haben, ich bin froh, daß ich es nicht zu tödten brauche, und weil gerade ein junger Frischling gelaufen kam, stach er den nieder, nahm Lunge und Leber heraus und bracht sie als Wahrzeichen der Königin mit, die kochte sie mit Salz und aß sie auf, und meinte sie hätte Sneewittchens Lunge und Le- ber gegessen.

Sneewittchen aber war in dem großen Wald mutterseelig allein, so daß ihm recht Angst ward und fing an zu laufen und zu lau- fen über die spitzen Steine, und durch die Dor- nen den ganzen Tag: endlich, als die Sonne untergehen wollte, kam es zu einem kleinen Häuschen. Das Häuschen gehörte sieben Zwer- gen, die waren aber nicht zu Haus, sondern in das Bergwerk gegangen. Sneewittchen ging hinein und fand alles klein, aber niedlich und reinlich: da stand ein Tischlein mit sieben kleinen Tellern, dabei sieben Löfflein, sieben Messerlein und Gäblein, sieben Becherlein, und an der Wand standen sieben Bettlein neben ein- ander ander frisch gedeckt. Sneewittchen war hungrig und durstig, aß von jedem Tellerlein ein wenig Gemüs und Brod, trank aus jedem Gläschen einen Tropfen Wein, und weil es so müd war, wollte es sich schlafen legen. Da probirte es die sieben Bettlein nach einander, keins war ihm aber recht, bis auf das siebente, in das legte es sich und schlief ein.

Wie es Nacht war, kamen die sieben Zwer- ge von ihrer Arbeit heim, und steckten ihre sie- ben Lichtlein an, da sahen sie, daß jemand in ihrem Haus gewesen war. Der erste sprach: „wer hat auf meinem Stühlchen gesessen?“ Der zweite: „wer hat von meinem Tellerchen gegessen?“ Der dritte: „wer hat von meinem Brödchen genommen?“ Der vierte: „wer hat von meinem Gemüschen gegessen?“ Der fünf- te: „wer hat mit meinem Gäbelchen gestochen?“ Der sechste: „wer hat mit meinem Messerchen geschnitten?“ Der siebente: „wer hat aus meinem Becherlein getrunken?“ Darnach sah der erste sich um und sagte: „wer hat in mein Bettchen getreten?“ Der zweite: „ei, in mei- nem hat auch jemand gelegen?“ und so alle weiter bis zum siebenten, wie der nach seinem Bettchen sah, da fand er das Sneewittchen darin liegen und schlafen. Da kamen die Zwer- ge alle gelaufen, und schrieen vor Verwunde- rung, und holten ihre sieben Lichtlein herbei, und betrachteten das Sneewittchen, „ei du mein Gott! ei du mein Gott! riefen sie, was ist das schön!“ Sie hatten große Freude an ihm, weckten es auch nicht auf, und ließen es in dem Bettlein liegen; der siebente Zwerg aber schlief bei seinen Gesellen, bei jedem eine Stun- de, da war die Nacht herum. Als nun Snee- wittchen aufwachte, fragten sie es, wer es sey und wie es in ihr Haus gekommen wäre, da erzählte es ihnen, wie seine Mutter es habe wollen umbringen, der Jäger ihm aber das Le- ben geschenkt, und wie es den ganzen Tag ge- laufen, und endlich zu ihrem Häuslein gekom- men sey. Da hatten die Zwerge Mitleiden und sagten: „wenn du unsern Haushalt versehen, und kochen, nähen, betten, waschen und stricken willst, auch alles ordentlich und reinlich halten, sollst du bei uns bleiben und soll dir an nichts fehlen; Abends kommen wir nach Haus, da muß das Essen fertig seyn, am Tage aber sind wir im Bergwerk und graben Gold, da bist du allein; hüt dich nur vor der Königin und laß niemand herein.“

Die Königin aber glaubte, sie sey wieder die allerschönste im Land, trat Morgens vor den Spiegel und fragte: „Spieglein, Spieglein an der Wand: wer ist die schönste Frau in dem ganzen Land?“ da antwortete der Spiegel aber wieder:

„Frau Königin, Ihr seyd die schönste hier: aber Sneewittchen, über den sieben Bergen ist noch tausendmal schöner als Ihr!“ wie die Königin das hörte erschrack sie und sah wohl, daß sie betrogen worden und der Jäger Sneewittchen nicht getödtet hatte. Weil aber niemand, als die sieben Zwerglein in den sieben Bergen war, da wußte sie gleich, daß es sich zu diesen gerettet hatte, und nun sann sie von neuem nach, wie sie es umbringen könnte, denn so lang der Spiegel nicht sagte, sie wär die schönste Frau im ganzen Land, hatte sie keine Ruh. Da war ihr alles nicht sicher und ge- wiß genug, und sie verkleidete sich selber in ei- ne alte Krämerin, färbte ihr Gesicht, daß sie auch kein Mensch erkannte, und ging hinaus vor das Zwergenhaus. Sie klopfte an die Thür und rief: „macht auf, macht auf, ich bin die alte Krämerin, die gute Waare feil hat.“ Sneewittchen guckte aus dem Fenster: „was habt ihr denn?“ „Schnürriemen, liebes Kind, sagte die Alte, und holte einen hervor, der war von gelber, rother und blauer Seide geflochten: „willst du den haben?“ Ei ja, sprach Sneewittchen, und dachte die gute alte Frau kann ich wohl hereinlassen, die meints redlich; riegelte also die Thüre auf und handel- te sich den Schnürriemen. „Aber wie bist du so schlampisch geschnürt, sagte die Alte, komm ich will dich einmal besser schnüren.“ Sneewitt- chen stellte sich vor sie, da nahm sie den Schnür- riemen und schnürte und schnürte es so fest, daß ihm der Athem verging, und es für todt hinfiel. Darnach war sie zufrieden und ging fort.

Bald darauf ward es Nacht, da kamen die sieben Zwerge nach Haus, die erschracken recht, als sie ihr liebes Sneewittchen auf der Erde liegen fanden, als wär es todt. Sie ho- ben es in die Höhe, da sahen sie, daß es so fest geschnürt war, schnitten den Schnürriemen entzwei, da athmete es erst, und dann ward es wieder lebendig. „Das ist niemand gewesen, als die Königin, sprachen sie, die hat dir das Leben nehmen wollen, hüte dich und laß keinen Menschen mehr herein.

Die Königin aber fragte ihren Spiegel: „Spieglein, Spieglein an der Wand: wer ist die schönste Frau in dem ganzen Land?“ der Spiegel antwortete: „Frau Königin, Ihr seyd die schönste hier, aber Sneewittchen bei den sieben Zwergelchen ist tausendmal schöner als Ihr.“ Sie erschrack, daß das Blut ihr all zum Her- zen lief, da sie sah, daß Sneewittchen wieder lebendig geworden war. Darnach sann sie den ganzen Tag und die Nacht, wie sie es doch noch fangen wollte, und machte einen giftigen Kamm, verkleidete sich in eine ganz andere Ge- stalt, und ging wieder hinaus. Sie klopfte an die Thür, Sneewittchen aber rief: „ich darf niemand hereinlassen;“ da zog sie den Kamm hervor, und als Sneewittchen den blinken sah und es auch jemand ganz fremdes war, so machte es doch auf, und kaufte ihr den Kamm ab. „Komm ich will dich auch kämmen,“ sagte die Kräme- rin, kaum aber stack der Kamm dem Snee- wittchen in den Haaren, da fiel es nieder und war todt. „Nun wirst du liegen bleiben,“ sagte die Königin, und ihr Herz war ihr leicht geworden, und sie ging heim. Die Zwerge aber kamen zu rechter Zeit, sahen was geschehen, und zogen den giftigen Kamm aus den Haa- ren, da schlug Sneewittchen die Augen auf, und war wieder lebendig, und versprach den Zwergen, es wollte gewiß niemand mehr ein- lassen.

Die Königin aber stellte sich vor ihren Spiegel: „Spieglein, Spieglein an der Wand: wer ist die schönste Frau in dem ganzen Land!“ der Spiegel antwortete: „Frau Königin, Ihr seyd die schönste hier, aber Sneewittchen bei den sieben Zwergelchen ist tausendmal schöner als Ihr!“ Wie das die Königin wieder hörte, zitterte und bebte sie vor Zorn: „so soll das Sneewittchen noch sterben, und wenn es mein Leben kostet!“ Dann ging sie in ihre heimlichste Stube, und niemand durfte vor sie kommen, und da mach- te sie einen giftigen, giftigen Apfel, äußerlich war er schön und rothbäckig, und jeder der ihn sah, bekam Lust dazu. Darauf verkleidete sie sich als Bauersfrau, ging vor das Zwerghaus und klopfte an. Sneewittchen guckte und sag- te: „ich darf keinen Menschen einlassen, die Zwerge haben mirs bei Leibe verboten.“ „Nun, wenn Ihr nicht wollt, sagte die Bäuerin, kann ich euch nicht zwingen, meine Aepfel will ich schon los werden, da, einen will ich euch zur Probe schenken.“ „Nein, ich darf auch nichts geschenkt nehmen, die Zwerge wollens nicht haben.“ „Ihr mögt Euch wohl fürch- ten, da will ich den Apfel entzwei schneiden und die Hälfte essen, da den schönen rothen Backen sollt Ihr haben;“ der Apfel war aber so künstlich gemacht, daß nur die rothe Hälfte vergiftet war. Da sah Sneewittchen, daß die Bäuerin selber davon aß, und sein Gelüsten darnach ward immer größer, da ließ es sich end- lich die andere Hälfte durchs Fenster reichen, und biß hinein, kaum aber hatte es einen Bis- sen im Mund, so fiel es todt zur Erde.

Die Königin aber freute sich, ging nach Haus und fragte den Spiegel: „Spieglein, Spieglein an der Wand: wer ist die schönste Frau in dem ganzen Land?“ da antworte er: „Ihr, Frau Königin, seyd die schönste Frau im Land!“ „Nun hab ich Ruhe“ sprach sie, da ich wieder die schönste im Lande bin, und Sneewittchen wird diesmal wohl todt bleiben.“

Die Zwerglein kamen Abends aus den Berg- werken nach Haus, da lag das liebe Sneewitt- chen auf dem Boden und war todt. Sie schnür- ten es auf und sahen, ob sie nichts giftiges in seinen Haaren fänden, es half aber alles nichts, sie konnten es nicht wieder lebendig machen. Sie legten es auf eine Bahre, setzten sich alle sieben daran, weinten und weinten drei Tage lang, dann wollten sie es begraben, da sahen sie aber daß es noch frisch und gar nicht wie ein Todter aussah, und daß es auch seine schönen rothen Backen noch hatte. Da ließen sie einen Sarg von Glas machen, legten es hinein, daß man es recht sehen konnte, schrieben auch mit golde- nen Buchstaben seinen Namen darauf und sei- ne Abstammung, und einer blieb jeden Tag zu Haus und bewachte es.

So lag Sneewittchen lange, lange Zeit in dem Sarg und verweste nicht, war noch so weiß als Schnee, und so roth als Blut, und wenns die Aeuglein hätte können aufthun, wä- ren sie so schwarz gewesen wie Ebenholz, denn es lag da, als wenn es schlief. Einmal kam ein junger Prinz zu dem Zwergenhaus und wollte darin übernachten, und wie er in die Stube kam und Sneewittchen in dem Glas- sarg liegen sah, auf das die sieben Lichtlein so recht ihren Schein warfen, konnt er sich nicht satt an seiner Schönheit sehen, und las die goldene Inschrift und sah, daß es eine Königs- tochter war. Da bat er die Zwerglein, sie soll- ten ihm den Sarg mit dem todten Sneewitt- chen verkaufen, die wollten aber um alles Gold nicht; da bat er sie, sie mögten es ihm schen- ken, er könne nicht leben ohne es zu sehen, und er wolle es so hoch halten und ehren, wie sein Liebstes auf der Welt. Da waren die Zwerg- lein mitleidig und gaben ihm den Sarg, der Prinz aber ließ ihn in sein Schloß tragen, und ließ ihn in seine Stube setzen, er selber saß den ganzen Tag dabei, und konnte die Augen nicht abwenden; und wenn er aus mußte gehen und konnte Sneewittchen nicht sehen, ward er traurig, und er konnte auch keinen Bissen essen, wenn der Sarg nicht neben ihm stand. Die Diener aber, die beständig den Sarg herum- tragen mußten, waren bös darüber, und einer machte einmal den Sarg auf, hob Sneewitt- chen in die Höh und sagte: um so eines tod- ten Mädchens willen, werden wir den ganzen Tag geplagt,“ und gab ihm mit der Hand ei- nen Stumpf in den Rücken. Da fuhr ihm der garstige Apfelgrütz, den es abgebissen hatte, aus dem Hals, und da war Sneewittchen wie- der lebendig. Da ging es hin zu dem Prin- zen, der wußte gar nicht, was er vor Freuden thun sollte, als sein liebes Sneewittchen le- bendig war, und sie setzten sich zusammen an die Tafel und aßen in Freuden.

Auf den andern Tag ward die Hochzeit bestellt, und Sneewittchens gottlose Mutter, auch eingeladen. Wie sie nun am Morgen vor dem Spiegel trat und sprach: „Spieglein, Spieglein an der Wand: wer ist die schönste Frau in dem ganzen Land!“ da antwortete er: „Frau Königin, Ihr seyd die schönste hier, aber die junge Königin ist tausendmal schöner als Ihr!“ Als sie das hörte, erschrack sie, und es war ihr so Angst, so Angst, daß sie es nicht sagen konnte. Doch trieb sie der Neid, daß sie auf der Hochzeit die junge Königin sehen wollte, und wie sie ankam, sah sie, daß es Sneewitt- chen war; da waren eiserne Pantoffeln im Feuer glühend gemacht, die mußte sie anziehen und darin tanzen, und ihre Füße wurden jämmer- lich verbrannt, und sie durfte nicht aufhören bis sie sich zu todt getanzt hatte.

The Twelve Brothers

English Version

German Version

Once upon a time there were a king and a queen. They lived happily together and had twelve children, all boys. One day the king said to his wife, "If our thirteenth child, which you are soon going to bring into the world, is a girl, then the twelve others shall die, so that her wealth may be great, and so that she alone may inherit the kingdom."

Indeed, he had twelve coffins made. They were filled with wood shavings and each was fitted with a coffin pillow. He had them put in a locked room, and gave the key to the queen, ordering her to tell no one about them.

The mother sat and mourned the entire day, until the youngest son -- who was always with her, and who was named Benjamin after the Bible -- said to her, "Dear mother, why are you so sad?"

"Dearest child," she answered, "I cannot tell you."

However, he would not leave her in peace, until she unlocked the room and showed him the coffins, already filled with wood shavings.

Then she said, "My dearest Benjamin, your father had these coffins made for you and your eleven brothers. If I bring a girl into the world, you are all to be killed and buried in them."

As she spoke and cried, her son comforted her, saying, "Don't cry, dear mother. We will take care of ourselves and run away."

Then she said, Go out into the woods with your eleven brothers. One of you should climb the highest tree that you can find. Keep watch there and look toward the castle tower. If I give birth to a little son, I will raise a white flag. If I give birth to a little daughter, I will raise a red flag, and then you should escape as fast as you can, and may God protect you. I will get up every night and pray for you, in the winter that you may warm yourselves near a fire, and in the summer that you may not suffer from the heat."

After she had blessed her children, they went out into the woods. One after the other of them kept watch, sitting atop the highest oak tree and looking toward the tower. After eleven days had passed, and it was Benjamin's turn, he saw that a flag had been raised. It was not the white one, but instead the red blood-flag, decreeing that they all were to die.

When the boys heard this they became angry and cried out, "Are we to suffer death for the sake of a girl! We swear that we will take revenge. Wherever we find a girl, her red blood shall flow."

Then they went deeper into the woods, and in its middle, where it was darkest, they found a little bewitched house that was empty.

They said, "We will live here. You, Benjamin, you are the youngest and weakest. You shall stay at home and keep house. We others will go and get things to eat."

Thus they went into the woods and shot rabbits, wild deer, birds, and doves, and whatever they could eat. These they brought to Benjamin, and he had to prepare them to satisfy their hunger. They lived together in this little house for ten years, but the time passed quickly for them.

The little daughter that their mother, the queen, had given birth to was now grown up. She had a good heart, a beautiful face, and a golden star on her forehead.

Once on a large washday she saw twelve men's shirts in the laundry and asked her mother, "Whose are these twelve shirts? They are much too small for father."

The queen answered with a heavy heart, "Dear child, they belong to your twelve brothers."

The girl said, "Where are my twelve brothers? I have never even heard of them."

She answered, "Only God knows where they are. They are wandering about in the world."

Then she took the girl, unlocked the room for her, and showed her the twelve coffins with the wood shavings and the coffin pillows.

"These coffins," she said, "were intended for your brothers, but they secretly ran away before you were born," and she told her how everything had happened.

Then the girl said, "Dear mother, don't cry. I will go and look for my brothers."

Then she took the twelve shirts and went forth into the great woods. She walked the entire day, in the evening coming to the bewitched little house.

She went inside and found a young lad, who asked, "Where do you come from, and where are you going?"

He was astounded that she was so beautiful, that she was wearing royal clothing, and that she had a star on her forehead.

"I am a princess and am looking for my twelve brothers. I will walk on as long as the sky is blue, until I find them." She also showed him the twelve shirts that belonged to them.

Benjamin saw that it was his sister, and said, "I am Benjamin, your youngest brother."

She began to cry for joy, and Benjamin did so as well. They kissed and embraced one another with great love.

Then he said, "Dear sister, I must warn you that we have agreed that every girl whom we meet must die."

She said, "I will gladly die, if I can thus redeem my twelve brothers."

"No," he answered, "you shall not die. Sit under this tub until our eleven brothers come, and I will make it right with them."

She did this, and when night fell they came home from the hunt. As they sat at the table eating, they asked, "What is new?"

Benjamin said, "Don't you know anything?"

"No," they answered.

He continued speaking, "You have been in the woods while I stayed at home, but I know more than you do."

"Then tell us," they shouted.

He answered, "If you will promise me that the next girl we meet shall not be killed."

"Yes," they all shouted. "We will show her mercy. Just tell us."

Then he said, "Our sister is here," and lifted up the tub. The princess came forth in her royal clothing and with the golden star on her forehead, so beautiful, delicate, and fine.

They all rejoiced, falling around her neck and kissing her, and they loved her with all their hearts.

Now she stayed at home with Benjamin and helped him with the work. The eleven went into the woods and captured wild game, deer, birds, and doves, so they would have something to eat. Their sister and Benjamin prepared it all. They gathered wood for cooking, herbs for the stew, and put the pot onto the fire so a meal was always ready when the eleven came home. She also kept the house in order, and made up the beds white and clean. The brothers were always satisfied, and they lived happily with her.

One time the two of them had prepared a good meal at home, and so they sat together and ate and drank and were ever so happy. Now there was a little garden next to the bewitched house, and in it there were twelve lilies, the kind that are called "students." Wanting to bring some pleasure to her brothers, she picked the twelve flowers, intending to give one to each of them when they were eating. But in the same instant that she picked the flowers, the twelve brothers were transformed into twelve ravens, and they flew away above the woods. The house and the garden disappeared as well.

Now the poor girl was alone in the wild woods. Looking around, she saw an old women standing next to her.

The old woman said, "My child, what have you done?" Why did you not leave the twelve white flowers standing? Those were your brothers, and now they have been transformed into ravens forever."

The girl said, crying, "Is there no way to redeem them?"

"No," said the old woman, "There is only one way in the world, and it is so difficult that you will never redeem them. You must remain silent for seven whole years, neither speaking nor laughing. If you speak a single word, even if all but one hour of the seven years has passed, then it will all be for nothing, and your brothers will be killed by that one word."

Then the girl said in her heart, "I know for sure that I will redeem my brothers."

She went and found a tall tree and climbed to its top, where she sat and span, without speaking and without laughing.

Now it came to pass that a king was hunting in these woods. He had a large greyhound that ran to the tree where the girl was sitting. It jumped about, yelping and barking up the tree. The king came, saw the beautiful princess with the golden star on her forehead, and was so enchanted by her beauty that he shouted up to her, asking her to become his wife. She gave him no answer, but nodded with her head. Then he himself climbed the tree, carried her down, set her on his horse, and took her home with him.

Their wedding was celebrated with great pomp and joy, but the bride neither spoke nor laughed.

After they had lived a few years happily together, the king's mother, who was a wicked woman, began to slander the young queen, saying to the king, "You have brought home a common beggar woman for yourself. Who knows what kind of godless things she is secretly doing. Even if she is a mute and cannot speak, she could at least laugh. Anyone who does not laugh has an evil conscience."

At first the king did not want to believe this, but the old woman kept it up so long, accusing her of so many wicked things, that the king finally let himself be convinced, and he sentenced her to death.

A great fire was lit in the courtyard, where she was to be burned to death. The king stood upstairs at his window, looking on with crying eyes, for he still loved her dearly. She had already been bound to the stake, and the fire was licking at her clothing with its red tongues, when the last moment of the seven years passed.

A whirring sound was heard in the air, and twelve ravens approached, landing together. As they touched the earth, it was her twelve brothers, whom she had redeemed. They ripped the fire apart, put out the flames, and freed their sister, kissing and embracing her.

Now that she could open her mouth and speak, she told the king why she had remained silent and had never laughed.

The king rejoiced to hear that she was innocent, and they all lived happily together until they died. The wicked stepmother was brought before the court and placed in a barrel filled with boiling oil and poisonous snakes, and she died an evil death.

Es war einmal ein König, der hatte zwölf Kinder, das waren lauter Buben, er wollte auch kein Mädchen haben und sagte zur Köni- gin: „wenn das dreizehnte Kind, das du zur Welt bringst, ein Mädchen ist, so laß ich die zwölf andern tödten, ists aber auch ein Bube, dann sollen sie alle miteinander leben bleiben.“ — Die Königin gedachte es ihm auszureden. Der König wollte aber nichts weiter hören: „wenns so ist, wie ich gesagt habe, so müssen sie ster- ben, lieber hau' ich ihnen selber den Kopf ab, als daß ein Mädchen darunter wäre.“

Da war die Königin traurig, denn sie hat- te ihre Söhne von Herzen lieb und wußte nicht, wie sie zu retten waren. Endlich ging sie zu dem jüngsten, den sie vor allen lieb hatte, of- fenbarte ihm, was der König beschlossen, und sagte: „allerliebstes Kind, geh du mit deinen eilf Brüdern hinaus in den Wald, da bleibt und kommt nicht nach Haus, einer von euch aber halte immer Wacht auf einem Baum und sehe nach dem Thurm hier, wenn ich ein Söhn- chen zur Welt bringe, will ich obenauf eine weiße Fahne stecken, ists aber ein Töchterchen eine rothe, und wenn ihr das seht, dann rettet euch, flieht in die weite Welt, und der liebe Gott behüt euch. Alle Nacht will ich aufste- hen und für euch beten, wenns kalt ist im Win- ter, daß ihr nicht friert und ein warmes Feuer vor euch brennt, und wenns heiß ist im Som- mer, daß ihr in einem kühlen Walde ruht und schlaft.“

So gesegnete sie die Kinder und sie gingen fort in den Wald. Oft guckten sie nach dem Thurm, und einer mußte beständig auf einer hohen Eiche sitzen und Acht haben. Bald auch wurde eine Fahne aufgesteckt, es war aber nicht die weiße, sondern die rothe Blutfahne, die ih- nen den Untergang drohte. Wie die Buben sie erblickten, wurden sie alle zornig und riefen: „sollen wir eines Mädchens willen das Leben verlieren!“ da schwuren sie zusammen, mitten in dem Wald zu bleiben, und aufzupassen, wenn sich ein Mädchen sehen ließ, wollten sie es ohne Gnade tödten.

Darauf suchten sie eine Höhle, wo der Wald am dunkelsten war, wo sie wohnten. Alle Morgen zogen elf hinaus auf die Jagd, einer mußte aber zu Haus bleiben, kochen, und den Haushalt führen. Jedes Mädchen aber, das den eilfen begegnete, war ohne Barmherzigkeit verloren; das dauerte viele Jahre.

Das Schwesterchen zu Haus aber ward groß und blieb das einzige Kind. Einmal hat- te es große Wäsche, darunter waren auch zwölf Mannshemden. „Für wen sind denn diese Hemder, fragte die Prinzessin, meinem Vater sind sie doch viel zu klein,“ da erzählte ihr die Wäscherin, daß sie zwölf Brüder gehabt hätte, die wären heimlich fortgegangen, kein Mensch wisse wohin, weil sie der König habe wollen tödten lassen, und diesen zwölf Brüdern gehör- ten diese zwölf Hemder. Das Schwesterchen verwunderte sich, daß ihm niemals von seinen zwölf Brüdern etwas zu Ohren gekommen und wie es Nachmittags auf der Wiese saß und die Wäsche bleichte, da fielen ihm die Worte der Wäscherin wieder ein, und es ward nachdenk- sam, und endlich stieg es auf, nahm die zwölf Hemder und ging in den Wald hinein, wo sei- ne Brüder lebten.

Das Schwesterchen kam gerade zu der Höhle, wo sie ihre Wohnung hatten. Die eilf waren auf der Jagd und nur ein ein- ziger daheim, der kochen mußte. Wie der das Mädchen erblickte, faßte er es gleich, und holte sein Schwert: „knie nieder, dein ro- thes Blut muß den Augenblick fließen.“ Das Mädchen aber bat ihn: „lieber Herr, laßt mich leben, ich will bei euch bleiben und euch redlich dienen, ich will kochen und den Haushalt füh- ren.“ Es war gerade der jüngste Bruder, den erbarmte die Schönheit des Mädchens und er schenkte ihr das Leben. Wie die eilfe nach Haus kamen und sich verwunderten, ein Mädchen le- bendig in der Höhle zu finden, sagte er zu ih- nen: „liebe Brüder, dies Mädchen ist in die Höhle gekommen, und wie ich es niederhauen wollte, da bat es so sehr um sein Leben, es wollt uns treu dienen und den Haushalt füh- ren, daß ichs ihm geschenkt habe.“ Die an- dern gedachten, daß ihnen das vortheilhaft wä- re und daß sie nun alle zwölf auf die Jagd ausgehen könnten, und warens zufrieden. Da zeigte es ihnen die zwölf Hemdlein und sagte, es wär' ihre Schwester; darüber freuten sie sich alle, und waren froh, daß sie es nicht getödtet hatten.

Das Schwesterchen übernahm nun den Haushalt, und wenn die Brüder auf der Jagd waren, sammelte es Holz und Kräuter, stellte zu am Feuer, deckte die Bettlein hübsch weiß und rein, und thät alles unverdrossen und flei- ßig. Einmal geschah es, daß es fertig war mit aller Arbeit, da ging es in den Wald spazieren. Es kam an einen Platz, wo zwölf schöne hohe, weiße Lilien standen, und weil sie ihr so wohl gefielen, brach sie alle miteinander ab. Kaum aber war das geschehen, so stand eine alte Frau vor ihr: „ach meine Tochter, sagte sie, warum hast du die zwölf Studentenblumen nicht ste- hen lassen! das sind deine zwölf Brüder, die sind nun alle in Raben verwandelt worden und sind verloren auf ewig.“ Das Schwesterchen fing an zu weinen, „ach!“ sagte es, „giebts denn kein Mittel sie zu erlösen?“ „Nein, es ist kein Mittel auf der Welt, als ein einziges, das ist so schwer, das du sie nicht damit befreien wirst: du mußt zwölf ganzer Jahr stumm seyn, sprichst du ein einziges Wort, und es fehlt nur eine Stunde daran, so ist alles umsonst und deine Brüder sind in dem Augenblick todt.“

Das Schwesterchen setzte sich da auf einen hohen Baum im Wald und spann und wollte zwölf Jahre stumm sitzen, um seine Brüder zu erlösen. Es geschah aber, daß der König auf einer Jagd durch den Wald ritt, und als er an dem Baum vorbei kam, stand sein Hund still und bellte. Der König hielt nun, sah hin- auf und war ganz verwundert über die Schön- heit der Prinzessin. Er rief ihr zu, ob sie sei- ne Gemahlin werden wollte. Sie schwieg aber still und nickte nur ein wenig mit dem Kopf. Da stieg der König selber hinauf und hob sie herunter, setzte sie vor sich auf sein Pferd und brachte sie heim in sein Schloß, wo die Hochzeit prächtig gehalten ward. Die Prin- zessin sprach aber niemals ein Wort und der König glaubte sie sey stumm. Doch hätten sie vergnügt mit einander gelebt, wenn nicht die Mutter des Königs gewesen wäre, die fing an die Königin bei ihrem Sohn zu verläum- den: „es ist ein gemeines Bettelmädchen, das du aus der Fremde mitgebracht hast, die hin- ter deinem Rücken die schändlichsten Dinge treibt.“ Weil die Königin nun sich nicht ver- theidigen konnte, ließ sich der König verführen, und glaubte ihr endlich und verurtheilte sie zum Tod. Da ward ein großes Feuer angemacht im Hof, darin sollte sie verbrannt werden. Schon stand sie in den Flammen und die spiel- ten an ihrem Kleide; da war eben die letzte Minute von den zwölf Jahren verflossen, man hörte in der Luft ein Geräusch, und es kamen zwölf Raben hergeflogen und ließen sich nieder. Wie sie die Erde berührten, waren es zwölf schöne Prinzen, die rissen das Feuer von ein- ander und führten ihre Schwester heraus. Da sprach sie ihr erstes Wort wieder und sagte dem König alles, wie es zugegangen und sie die zwölf Brüder habe erlösen müssen; und sie waren alle vergnügt, daß es so wohl gewor- den war.

Was sollten sie mit der bösen Stiefmutter anfangen; sie ward in ein Faß gesteckt von sie- dendem Oehl und von giftigen Schlangen an- gefüllt, und starb da eines bösen Todes.

overview of our project

Our project consists of a thorough analysis of the Grimm Fairy Tales in order to find connections between the "good" vs. the "evil" mother-figure. In order to do this, we characterized and tagged all women mentioned, tagged all actions,and tagged all dialogue. Our main goals were:

What types of women figures are represented and what defines them?
Find differences between the "good" vs the "evil" mother-figure.
Does the English version accurately translate the 1812 German text?
If there are differences, what are they?

Our analysis of the ten different German and the translated English Tales allowed us to answer some of these questions and to pose a few more.

our team

About the Developers

Regis Curtis is triple majoring in German, French, and West European Studies. He joined this class to "STEMify" his humanities education. His favorite Grimms' Fairy Tale is "Cinderella" because he loves the Disney dichotomy.

Darian McGinnis is a Computer Science Major. She joined this class because she wanted to expand her computer science skills. Her favorite Grimms' Fairy Tale is "Little Red Cap" beause of it's wholesome ending.

Victoria Costa is a non-traditional student majoring in English Literature and minoring in Film Studies. She took this class because she thought it might be a good elective for someone potientially studying Library Science in grad school. Her favorite Grimms' Fairy Tale is "Little Snow White", if only because the Disney version inspired a great Miles Davis record.

Alexis Moffa is an Architectural Studies major. She joined this class to expand her technological skills and learn applications of this in the real world. Her favorite Grimms' Fairy Tale is "Hansel and Gretel", for it holds a special place in her heart as she once played Hansel in a play.

Marion Riley (TA) is a Linguistics and Religious Studies major. Her favorite thing about being a TA for this course is helping students problem solve their code and getting that "aha!" moment when something works! Her favorite Grimms' Fairy Tale is "Snow White and Rose Red".

The team wishes to extend a special thank you to our professor, Dr. David Birnbaum, and the rest of the instructional team, for their guidance and support throughout the development of this project.